<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true relation of the unjust, cruel, and barbarous proceedings against the English, at Amboyna in the East-Indies, by the Netherlandish Governour &amp; Council there. Also the copie of a pamphlet of the Dutch in defence of the action. With remarks upon the whole matter. Published by authoritie.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1651</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 202 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 103 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A95286</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T3065</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1311_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209171</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868061</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868061</idno>
            <idno type="VID">169753</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A95286)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 169753)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 175:E1311[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true relation of the unjust, cruel, and barbarous proceedings against the English, at Amboyna in the East-Indies, by the Netherlandish Governour &amp; Council there. Also the copie of a pamphlet of the Dutch in defence of the action. With remarks upon the whole matter. Published by authoritie.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[30], 64, [4], 33, [1], 58, 14 p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Will. Bentley, for Will. Hope, at the Anchor under S. Bartholowmew Church near the Royal Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno Domini 1651.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The 'pamphlet of the Dutch in defence' has its own titlepage which reads: A true declaration of the news that came out of the East-Indies, with the Pinnace called the Hare, arrived in Texel in June, 1624.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Nouemb 23".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Dutch --  Indonesia --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Ambon Island (Indonesia) --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>British --  Indonesia --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:169753:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>A True RELATION of the UNJUST, CRUEL and BARBAROUS <hi>PROCEEDINGS</hi> againſt the ENGLISH at AMBOYNA In the <hi>Eaſt-Indies,</hi> by the Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landiſh GOVERNOUR &amp; COUNCIL there. Alſo the Copie of a Pamphlet of the <hi>Dutch</hi> in Defence of the <hi>Action.</hi> With <hi>Remarks</hi> upon the whole matter.</p>
                  <p>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="license">
                        <body>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Publiſhed by Authoritie.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by WILL. BENTLEY, for <hi>Will. Hope,</hi> at the <hi>Anchor</hi> under S. <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholomew</hi> Church near the Royal <hi>Exchange, Anno Domini</hi> 1651.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="frontispiece">
                  <pb facs="tcp:169753:2"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>depiction of scenes of torture and execution: a half-naked man hanging stretched in an X on a door frame, his face bound, while a man on a stool pours water over his head and another man tickles him under the arm with feathers; a second half-naked man kneeling in prayer with his hands bound while another man stands behind him with a drawn sword raised to strike; a third half-naked man sitting on the ground</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:169753:2"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:169753:3"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:169753:3"/>
                  <head>To his EXCELLENCIE The LORD GENERAL CROMWEL.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>My Lord,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ee here a piece of Babariſm, which hath lain ſo long both as an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurie, and a dishonour to our Nation brought again to light, by which, as we may compare the difference of theſe bleſſed times, from thoſe unhappie ones when this was acted and paſſed by; ſo we muſt needs remember to bleſs God
<pb facs="tcp:169753:4"/>for that victorious hand of yours, which hath in ſo great a manner led us a good part out of the Wilderneſs; And therefore I thought it but a piece of publick gratitude, (beſides private) to throw it as your Excellencies feet; whoſe great ſoul, I preſume, will rather deſcend to look into this buſineſs, wherein your Countrey is ſo highly concerned, that in reſpect a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad you have been a fierie wall about her, ſo at home you are become her great <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence,</hi> and guid thoſe great motions of her peace and ſecuritie: Which great work, as I hope God will grant you to ſee finiſhed, ſo wiſh I you may live long to enjoy the fruits and comfort of it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:169753:4"/>
                  <head>AN ADVERTISEMENT TO THE READER.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F we conſider how loud and preſſing the crie of bloud is, or with what high ſeverity God ever proceeds againſt it, though his wrath for ſome ſmall time may ſeem to be aſleep, we have juſt cauſe to fear, that there is a heavy account muſt be given by the <hi>Dutch</hi> for that execra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Tyrannie of theirs exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted
<pb facs="tcp:169753:5"/>upon the bodies of ſeveral <hi>Engliſh</hi> at <hi>Amboyna.</hi> To take away any mans life without due courſe of Juſtice, though it be with the greateſt civility and ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs of death that could be, is a crime which God hath denounced murder, and will viſit accordingly; but to heighten and multiply a death with all the previous Tortures that a paſſionate Diabolical malice can in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent, cruelty inflict, or the frame of mans body under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go, is ſo far from being manly or Chriſtian, that it is beyond ſavageneſs and beſtiality, and approches that accurſed frame of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit that he hath plundged himſelf into, who ſits in the ſeat of darkneſs.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:169753:5"/>
                  <p>For my part as I delight not to be curious in theſe ſpeculations, which acquaint the mind with extremities and Criticiſms of ſin, ſo it is a grief that the Theory of wickedneſs ſhould be ſo much enlarged as it would be by the treatiſe which thou haſt in thy hands; Which, as it hath bruitiſhly out-done all former records and examples of cruelty, ſo it may unluckily poſſibly ſerve for inſtruction to ſome future inventive and poiſoned ſpirits. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed as I wiſh the occaſion of publiſhing of it had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver been, ſo do I wiſh ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice once required and had, that the remembrance of it might have been buried. But the breach being ſo na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional,
<pb facs="tcp:169753:6"/>and to this day un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatisfied, and the bloud there ſpilt no doubt crying loud, it had been injuſtice in us to have buried it in ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and not diſplayed it to the ſun. For as the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of thoſe Torments were from a cauſeleſs and and ſlight ſuſpition of an improbable and ineffective plot, ſo by that means were we forced from our poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions in thoſe parts, and the injury became complicated, both as againſt juſtice and intereſt.</p>
                  <p>True it is that the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Company made the moſt diligent addreſſes to King <hi>James</hi> for revenge that could be, but that bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing Star of Fortune, that was after removed by a
<pb facs="tcp:169753:6"/>ſtab, prepoſſeſſed by a great ſum of money, interpoſed between the judgement of that King, and over-ruled his affection, ſo that he, who was naturally un-active and drouſie enough, being lull'd by ſuch a <hi>privado,</hi> fel aſleep, and ſnorted out the reſt of his idle reign in debauchery and ſilence. The <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Company ſeing themſelves obſtructed in the proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, thought fit to preſerve the memorie of ſuch a but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery, by getting the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Tortures done at large in Oyl, but the Table was ſcarce ſooner hung up, but the Murderers began to fear it would bleed at the noſe; ſo that <hi>Buckingham</hi> was appeaſed by another ſacrifice, and the Picture
<pb facs="tcp:169753:7"/>commanded to be taken down.</p>
                  <p>In King <hi>Charles</hi>'s time the buſineſs was not ſtirred in, he had too great deſigns at home, than to preſerve our Honour, or remedy our injuries abroad; but now ſince that yoak of Kingſhip is taken off our necks, me thinks we ſhould like men, whoſe ſhackles are taken off them while they are aſleep, leap up nimbly, and make uſe of our Liberty. It were the moſt irrational thing in the World to think of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving of them, who, though they received aſſiſtance from us in their greateſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction and loweſt miſerie, have refuſed not onely to aſſiſt us now, when their caſe is ours, but have been
<pb facs="tcp:169753:7"/>more than neutral againſt us, jealous, it ſhould ſeem, that their way of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which they have ſo grown and thriven under, ſhould have the ſame effects with us. But I hope God will give us hearts to make uſe of the advantages in our hands, and perſiſt in doing wonderfull things for us. And as he hath brought us out of the deſart in ſo high and fearfull a manner, ſo no doubt if we walk anſwerably, we ſhall ſee his countenance ſhine upon us, and improve this bleſſed peace at home, to make good our peace abroad, and ſo by his good aſſiſtance en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy ſuch earthly bleſſings, as may render us ſafe, if not terrible to the Nations round about us.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Grayes-Inne.</hi> 
                        <date>Sept. 10. 1651.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:169753:8"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:169753:8"/>
                  <head>To the READER.</head>
                  <p>GEntle Reader, thou mayeſt (perhaps) won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der why this Relation of the buſineſs of <hi>Amboyna,</hi> ſo many Moneths ſince taken upon the Oaths and depoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of our people that came thence, and preſented to his Majeſty, and the Lords of his Privy Councel, cometh now at laſt to the Preſs, and was not either ſooner pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed, or altogether ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed. The truth is, the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Eaſt-India Company have ever been very tender of the ancient amity and
<pb facs="tcp:169753:9"/>good correſpondence held be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween this Realm and the Neatherlands, and have been very loath, by divulging of the private injuries done them by the Neatherlands Eaſt-India Company, to give the least occaſion of any di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſt or disaffection, which might happily grow between theſe two Nations, for the ſake, and on the behalf of the two Companies reſpectively. For which cauſe, although the wrongs and injuries, or rather contumelies done unto the Engliſh by the Dutch in the Indies, have been as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolerable as manifold; as to ſay nothing of thoſe great heaps of them buried in the <hi>Amneſty</hi> of the Treaty of the year <hi>1619.</hi> and onely to point at the general heads of thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:169753:9"/>committed ſince that Treaty, and groſſely contrarie to the main intent, and expreſs words and diſpoſition of the ſame: first, in the point of hoſtility; the invaſion of the Iſlands of <hi>Lantore</hi> and <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laroone,</hi> then and before in the quiet poſſeſsion of the Engliſh, in the name of the Crown of England; the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the ſame Iſlands by force; the razing and demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing of the Engliſh Forts; the binding of the Engliſh (that had not ſo much as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted them) to ſtakes with ropes about their necks, throt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tling them with the ſame, and flouriſhing their naked ſwords about them, as if they would preſently have di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpatched them; then taking them ſo amazed and bound,
<pb facs="tcp:169753:10"/>and tumbling them down the rocks; and after, carrying their cruſhed and bruiſed car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſses away in irons: ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in the point of their uſurp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſovereignty; their taking upon them the Conuſance of controverſies between the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh and the Indians, for matters paſſed far without the compaſs of the Neather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands pretended juriſdiction, and executing their ſentences thereupon by plain force; ſeizing of the Engliſh Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies goods, fining, impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning, ſtocking, yea, whip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping our people at a post in the open market-place, and after, waſhing them with vinegar and ſalt: thirdly, in point of partnerſhip with the Engliſh, their putting great ſums to the common account;
<pb facs="tcp:169753:10"/>which were disburſed to the private and ſole behoof of the Dutch; giving great pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents for the glory of the Dutch, without conſent of the Engliſh, and making war for the inlargement of their own dominion, yet bringing the charge to the common ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count; together with infinite other the like, the particulars whereof would ariſe to a juſt and ample volume: Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs, the Engliſh Company from time to time contented themſelves with informing his Majeſtie, and his Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Privy Councel with their grievances privately in writing, to the end, that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary relief and reparation might be obtained, without publiſhing any thing to the World in print, thereby to
<pb facs="tcp:169753:11"/>ſtir up or breed ill bloud be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween theſe Nations, which are otherwiſe tied in ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny reciprocal obligations. And the ſame courſe they have hitherto holden alſo in this crying buſineſs of <hi>Amboyna;</hi> onely offering to the <hi>Manes</hi> of their mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered Countrey-men, Factors and Kinsfolks, their effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual endeavours in a duti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full courſe unto his Majeſty for juſtice for their innocent bloud, and reparation of the honour of the Nation herein intereſſed. In which their wonted way they were ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, that they could not be driven out of the ſame by the contrary courſe of ſome of the other party; that not glutted nor mollified with the bloud of theſe innocents, nor
<pb facs="tcp:169753:11"/>with all the other ſufferings of the Engliſh in the Indies, publiſhed a Pamphlet in print in the Neatherlands Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, not onely in justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of this barbarous butchery, but withall in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace of the Engliſh Nation, and the Laws and juſtice of the ſame. But behold now further, the ſame Pamphlet, being called in by an Edict of the States General, was yet afterwards tranſlated and printed in Engliſh, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperſed even in this Realm it ſelf, to brave and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace us at our own dores, and in our own language. This, no Engliſh patience can bear: the bloud of the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent cries out againſt it: the honour of the Nation ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in it. Wherefore the
<pb facs="tcp:169753:12"/>Engliſh Eaſt-India Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny is hereby inforced, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to their deſire and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom, to have recourſe alſo to the Preſs, to maintain the reputation of thoſe their Countrey-men and ſervants, that loſt their lives unjustly; and to acquaint the World with the naked truth of this cauſe, hitherto masked, muf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fled, and obſcured in a fog of factions, concealments, and crafty conveyances of the Author of this Pamphlet, and his clients, the Governour and Councel (ſo termed) of <hi>Amboyna.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Having thus acquainted thee, gentle Reader, with the reaſons why this buſineſs was no ſooner publiſhed in print, it remaineth yet further, that thou be ſatisfied in an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection
<pb facs="tcp:169753:12"/>or two more, which common reaſon will ſuggeſt unto thee. Without doubt, reading this diſcourſe, and being a true Patriot of thine own Countrey, and a well-willer of the Neatherlands (as we preſume and wiſh thee to be,) thou wilt wonder how it cometh to paſs, that our Nation, which hath not been wont to receive ſuch disgra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, ſhould now be ſo weak and unprovided in the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, as to ſuffer ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignities, and to be ſo groſly overtopped, outraged and vilified there? as alſo thou wilt no leſs admire, that any of the Netherlands Nation, which hath received ſuch and ſo many favours and ſupports from hence, and held ſo good and antient corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondence
<pb facs="tcp:169753:13"/>with our Nation, ſhould now offer and commit ſuch odious contumelies on Engliſh men, their partners, and allies by ſpecial Treaty. Herein thou wilt ſoon anſwer thy ſelf, if thou but conſider the different end and deſign of the Engliſh and Dutch Companies trading in the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, appearing by their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral courſe and practiſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectively. The Engliſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſubjects of a peaceable Prince, that hath enough of his own, and is therewith content, without affecting of new acqueſts; have aimed at nothing in their Eaſt-In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia Trade, but a Lawfull and competent gain by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce and Traffick with the people of thoſe parts. And although they have in ſome
<pb facs="tcp:169753:13"/>places builded Forts, and ſetled ſome ſtrength, yet that hath not been done by force or violence, againſt the good will of the Magiſtrates or people of the Countrey; but with their deſire, conſent, and good liking, for the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity onely of the Trade, and upon the ſaid Magiſtrate and peoples voluntary yielding themſelves under the obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience and Sovereignty of the Crown of England; their own ancient Laws, Cuſtoms and Priviledges, neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs reſerved. Further, the ſame Engliſh had undoubted confidence in the Neather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands Nation there alſo trading, eſpecially being late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conjoyned with them in the ſtrict alliance and ſocial confederacy of the year <hi>1619.</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:169753:14"/>and therefore attended no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing from them, but the offices of good affection and partnerſhip. Upon theſe grounds, the Engliſh Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany made their equipages anſwerable onely to a courſe of commerce and peaceable traffick; not expecting any hoſtility, neither from the Indians, nor eſpecially from the Dutch. On the other ſide, the Neatherlanders, from the beginning of their trade in the Indies, not contented with the ordinary courſe of a fair and free commerce, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaded divers Iſlands, took ſome Forts, built others, and laboured nothing more, than the conqueſts of Countries, and the acquiring of new do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion. By which reaſon, as they were accordingly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided
<pb facs="tcp:169753:14"/>of ſhipping, ſouldiers, and all warlike proviſion, as alſo of places of Rendevouz upon the ſhore, and thereby enabled to wrong the Engliſh as well as others: ſo the coſt and charges of their ſhipping, Forts, and Souldiers, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploied upon theſe deſigns, roſe to ſuch an height, as was not to be maintained by the trade they had in thoſe parts. Wherefore, for a ſupply, they were forced (as ſome of their own Countrey-men and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venturers in their Company, affirm) to fiſh with dry nets, that is to ſay, to pick quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels with the Indians, and ſo to take their ſhips, and make prize of their goods. Which yet not anſwering their charge and adventure, they proceeded alſo to quarrel with
<pb facs="tcp:169753:15"/>the Engliſh, to debar them of trade to free places; and for attempting ſuch trade, to take their ſhips and goods. Touching which, when a good order was ſet by the ſaid trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the year <hi>1619.</hi> yet they ſaw, they could not make their reckoning to any pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, unleſs they utterly drave the Engliſh out of the trade of thoſe parts; thereby to have the whole and ſole traffick of the commodities of the Indies in theſe parts of <hi>Europe,</hi> in their own hands; and ſo to make the price at their pleaſure, ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to maintain and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote their conqueſts, and withall to yield them an ample benefit of their trade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Which unleſs they can, by this and the like worry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:169753:15"/>and wearying of the Engliſh bring to paſs, it is eaſie to be judged by thoſe that understand any thing of the courſe and ſtate of the trade of thoſe parts, that albeit their returns hereafter ſhould prove as great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually, as of late extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily they have happened to be, yet the main ſtock and Eſtate of the Company must needs abate and decay by ſome hundred thouſands of pounds yearly. Thus, Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, thou ſeeſt what hath made us unprovided against ſuch accidents, and what now enforceth the Dutch Eaſt-India Company, or their ſervants in the Indies, againſt the common Genius of their Nation, and the wonted firm affection between theſe two
<pb facs="tcp:169753:16"/>Nations mutually, thus to degenerate, and break out into ſuch ſtrange and incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible outrages againſt their nearest allies and beſt deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving friends. <hi>Farewell.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="account">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:169753:16"/>
                  <head>A TRUE RELATION Of the late Unjuſt Cruel, and Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous proceedings againſt the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> at <hi>Amboyna</hi> in the <hi>Eaſt-Indies,</hi> by the <hi>Neatherlanders</hi> there, upon a forged pretence of a conſpiracie of the ſaid <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter the fruitleſs iſſue of two ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Treaties: the firſt Anno 1613. in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don;</hi> and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther An. 1615. at the <hi>Hague</hi> in Holland, touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the differences between the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Dutch</hi> in the <hi>Eaſt-Indies,</hi> at laſt by a third Treaty, Anno 1619. in <hi>London,</hi> there was a full and ſolemn compoſition made of all the ſaid differences, and a fair order ſet for the future
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:169753:17"/>proceeding of the Suppoſts of both Companies in the <hi>Indies,</hi> as well in the courſe of their Trade and commerce, as otherwiſe. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt ſundry other points, it was agreed, That in regard of the great bloud-ſhed and coſt, pretended to be beſtowed by the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> in winning of the Trade of the Iſles of the <hi>Molluc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cos, Banda,</hi> and <hi>Amboyna,</hi> from the <hi>Spaniards</hi> and <hi>Portugals,</hi> and in building of Forts for the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual ſecuring of the ſame, the ſaid <hi>Hollanders</hi> therefore ſhould enjoy two third parts of that Trade, and the <hi>Engliſh</hi> the other third; and the charge of the Forts to be maintained by Taxes and Impoſitions, to be levied upon the Merchandize. Wherefore in conſequence of this agreement, the <hi>Engliſh Eaſt-India</hi> Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny planted certain Factories for their ſhare of this Trade; ſome at the <hi>Molluccos,</hi> ſome at <hi>Banda,</hi> and ſome at <hi>Amboyna.</hi> Of the two former of theſe, there will be, at this preſent ſmall occaſion to ſpeak further; but the laſt will prove the Scene of a ſad Tragedy.</p>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:169753:17"/>
                  <p>This <hi>Amboyna</hi> is an Iſland ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing near <hi>Seran,</hi> of the circuit of forty leagues, and giveth name alſo to ſome other ſmall Iſlands adjacent. It beareth Cloves; for gathering and buying in whereof the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Company for their part had planted five ſeveral Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctories: the head and <hi>Rende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouz</hi> of all, at the Town of <hi>Amboyna;</hi> and therein firſt Maſter <hi>George Muſchamp,</hi> and afterward Maſter <hi>Gabriel Towerſon,</hi> their Agents with directions over the ſmaller Factories at <hi>Hitte</hi> and <hi>Larica</hi> upon the ſame Iſland, and at <hi>Loho</hi> and <hi>Cambello,</hi> upon a point of their neighbouring Iſland of <hi>Seran.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Upon theſe Iſlands of <hi>Amboyna,</hi> and the point of <hi>Seran,</hi> the Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landers have four Forts, the chief of all is at the ſaid Town of <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boyna,</hi> and is very ſtrong, having four Points or Bulwarks with their Curtains, and upon each of theſe Points ſix great pieces of Ordinance mounted, moſt of them of braſs. The one ſide of this Caſtle is waſhed by the Sea, and the other is divided from the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:169753:18"/>land with a Ditch of four or five fathom broad, very deep, and ever filled with the Sea The gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of this Caſtle conſiſteth of about 200 <hi>Dutch</hi> Souldiers and a Company of free Burgers. Beſides theſe, there is always a matter of three or four hundred <hi>mardikers</hi> (for ſo they uſually call the free Natives) in the Town, ready to ſerve the Caſtle at an hours warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. There lie alſo in the road (for the moſt part) diverſe good Ships of the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> as well for the guard of the place by Sea, as for the occaſions of Traffick: this being the chief Rendevouz, as well for the <hi>Iſland</hi> of <hi>Banda,</hi> as for the reſt of <hi>Amboyna.</hi> Here the <hi>Engliſh</hi> lived; not in the Caſtle, but under protection thereof, in a houſe of their own in the Town; holding themſelves ſafe, as well in reſpect of the ancient bonds of amity between both Nations, as of the ſtrict conjunction made by the late Treaty before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned.</p>
                  <p>They continued here ſome two years, converſing and trading to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> by
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:169753:18"/>vertue of the ſaid Treaty. In which time there fell out ſundry differences and debates between them: The <hi>Engliſh</hi> complaining that the <hi>Hollanders</hi> did not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly laviſh away much money in building, and unneceſſary ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pences, upon the Forts and other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, and bring large and unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable reckonings thereof to the common account; but alſo did, for their part, pay the Garriſons with victuals and cloath of <hi>Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mondell,</hi> which they put off to the Souldiers at three or four times the value it coſt them, yet would not allow of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Companies part of the ſame charge, but onely in ready mony; thereby drawing from the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> (which ought to pay but one third part) more than two thirds of the whole true charge. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, and upon the like occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, grew ſome diſcontents and diſputes, and the complaints were ſent to <hi>Jaccatra,</hi> in the Iſland of <hi>Java Major,</hi> to the Councel of defence of both Nations there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiding: who alſo, not agreeing upon the points in difference,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:169753:19"/>ſent the ſame hither over into <hi>Europe,</hi> to be decided by both Companies here; or, in default of their agreement, by the Kings Majeſty, and the Lords the States General, according to an Article of the Treatie of the year 1619. on this behalf. In the mean time the diſcontent between the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> and the <hi>Dutch,</hi> about theſe and other differences, continued, and dayly encreaſed, untill at laſt there was a ſword found, to cut in ſunder that knot at once, which the tedious diſputes of <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boyna</hi> and <hi>Jaccatra</hi> could not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. And this was uſed in man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as followeth.</p>
                  <p>About the eleventh of <hi>Februa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> 1622. <hi>Stilo veteri.</hi> a <hi>Japoner</hi> Souldier of the <hi>Dutch</hi> in their Caſtle of <hi>Amboyna,</hi> walking in the night upon the wall, came to the Sentinel (being a <hi>Hollander,</hi>) and there, amongſt other talk, asked him ſome queſtions touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſtrength of the Caſtle, and the people that were therein. It is here to be noted, that thoſe <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poners</hi> (of whom there is not thirty in all the Iſland) did, for
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:169753:19"/>the moſt part, ſerve the Dutch as Souldiers, yet were not of their truſty bands always lodged in the Caſtle, but upon occaſion called out of the Town to aſſiſt in the watch. This <hi>Japoner</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, was for his ſaid confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence with the Sentinel appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended upon ſuſpition of Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and put to the Torture. Thereby (as ſome of the <hi>Dutch</hi> affirmed) he was brought to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs himſelf, and ſundry others of his Countrey-men there, to have contrived the taking of the Caſtle. Hereupon, other <hi>Japoners</hi> were examined and Tortured, as alſo a Portugal, the Guardian of the Slaves under the <hi>Dutch.</hi> Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring this examination, which continued three or four dayes; ſome of the <hi>Engliſh-men</hi> went to and from the Caſtle upon their buſineſs, ſaw the priſoners, heard of their tortures, &amp; of the crime laid to their charge; But all this while ſuſpected not, that this matter did any whit concern themſelves, having never had any converſation with the <hi>Japoners,</hi> nor with the <hi>Portugal</hi> aforeſaid.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:169753:20"/>At the ſame time there was one <hi>Abel Price,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Abel Price</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined.</note> Chirurgion of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> priſoner in the Caſtle, for offering in his drunkenneſs to ſet a <hi>Dutch</hi> mans houſe on fire. This fellow the <hi>Dutch</hi> took, and ſhewed him ſome of the <hi>Japo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners,</hi> whom they had firſt moſt grievouſly tortured, and told him, they had confeſſed the <hi>Engliſh</hi> to have been of their confedera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie for the taking of the Caſtle; and that if he would not confeſs the ſame, they would uſe him even as they had done theſe <hi>Japo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners,</hi> and worſe alſo. Having gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him the Torture, they ſoon made him confeſs what ever they asked him. This was the ſifteenth of <hi>February</hi> 1622. <hi>Stilo veteri.</hi> Forthwith, about nine of the clock the ſame morning, they ſent for Captain <hi>Towerſon,</hi> and the reſt of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> that were in the Town to come to ſpeak with the Governour in the Caſtle: They all went, ſave one that was left to keep the houſe. Being come to the Governour, he told Captain <hi>Towerſon,</hi> that himſelf and others of his Nation were accuſed of a
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:169753:20"/>conſpiracie to ſurpriſe the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, and therefore, until further Trial, were to remain priſoners. Inſtantly alſo they attached him that was left at home in the houſe, took the Marchandize of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Company there in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their own cuſtody by Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie, and ſeized all the Cheſts, Boxes, Books, Writings, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> houſe. Captain <hi>Towerſon</hi> was commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to his Chamber with a guard of <hi>Dutch</hi> Souldiers. <hi>Emmanuel Tomſon</hi> was kept priſoner in the Caſtle; the reſt, viz <hi>John Beo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mont, Edward Collins, William Webber, Ephraim Ramſey, Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Johnſon, John Fardo,</hi> and <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Brown</hi> were ſent aboard the <hi>Hollanders</hi> Ships then riding in Harbour, ſome to one Ship, and ſome to another, and all made faſt in Irons. The ſame day al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the Governour ſent to the two other Factories in the ſame Iſland, to apprehend the reſt of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> there. So that <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel Colſon, John Clark, George Sharrock,</hi> that were found in the Factorie at <hi>Hitto,</hi> and <hi>Edward
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:169753:21"/>Collins, William Webber,</hi> and <hi>John Sadler</hi> at <hi>Larica,</hi> were all brought priſoners to <hi>Amboyna,</hi> the ſixteenth of <hi>February.</hi> Upon which day alſo <hi>John Powl, John Wetheral,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Ladbrook,</hi> were apprehended at <hi>Cambello,</hi> and <hi>John Beomont, William Grigs,</hi> and <hi>Ephraim Ramſey,</hi> at <hi>Loho,</hi> and brought in irons to <hi>Amboyna</hi> the twentieth of the ſame moneth. In the mean time the Governour and Fiſcal went to work with the priſoners that were already there: And firſt they ſent for <hi>Iohn Beomont,</hi> and <hi>Timothy Iohnſon,</hi> from aboard the <hi>Unicorn;</hi> who being come into the Caſtle, <hi>Beomont</hi> was left with a guard in the Hall, and <hi>Iohnſon</hi> was taken into an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other room. Where, by and by, <hi>Beomont</hi> heard him crie out ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry pitifully; then to be quiet for a little while, and then loud again. After taſte of the torture, <hi>Abel Price</hi> the Chirurgion, that firſt was examined and tortured (as is above remembred) was brought in to confront and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe him: But <hi>Iohnſon</hi> not yet
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:169753:21"/>confeſſing any thing, <hi>Price</hi> was quickly carried out, and <hi>John<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> brought again to the torture; where <hi>Beomont</hi> heard him ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time crie aloud, then quiet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, then roar afreſh. At laſt, after he had been about an hour in this ſecond examination, he was brought forth wailing and lamenting, all wet, and cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly burnt in divers parts of his body, and ſo laid aſide in a by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>place of the Hall, with a Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier to watch him that he ſhould ſpeak with no body.
<note place="margin">Emanuel Tomſon <hi>examined.</hi>
                     </note> Then was <hi>Emanuel Tomſon</hi> brought to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination; not in the room where <hi>Johnſon</hi> had been, but in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, ſomething farther from the Hall. Yet <hi>Beomont</hi> being in the Hall, heard him roar moſt lamentably, and many times. At laſt, after an hour and an half ſpent in torturing him, he was carried away into another room another way, ſo that he came not by <hi>Beomont</hi> through the Hall. Next, was <hi>Beomont</hi> called in, and being demanded many things, all which he denied with deep Oaths and proteſtations,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:169753:22"/>was made faſt to be Tortured, a cloath tied about his neck, and two men ready with their Jarres of water to be poured on his head. But yet for this time the Governour bad looſe him, he would ſpare him a day or two, becauſe he was an old man. This was all Saturdays work, the fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth of <hi>February</hi> aforeſaid.</p>
                  <p>Upon Sunday the ſixteenth of <hi>February, William Webber, Edward Collins, Ephraim Ramſey,</hi> and <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Brown,</hi> were fetcht from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>board the <hi>Rotterdam,</hi> to be exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined. At the ſame time came <hi>Samuel Colſon, William Grigs,</hi> and <hi>John Clark, George Sharrock,</hi> and <hi>Iohn Sadler,</hi> from <hi>Hitto</hi> and <hi>Lari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca,</hi> and were immediately, upon their arrival, brought into the Caſtle Hall.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Robert Brown Tailor</hi> was firſt called in;
<note place="margin">Robert Brown <hi>examined.</hi>
                     </note> and being tormented with water, confeſſed all in order as the Fiſcal asked him.</p>
                  <p>Then was <hi>Edward Collins</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in,
<note place="margin">Edward Collins <hi>examined.</hi>
                     </note> and told, that thoſe that were formerly examined, had confeſt him as acceſſarie to the plot of taking the Caſtle. Which,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:169753:22"/>when he denied with great Oaths and execrations, they made his hands and feet faſt to the Rack, bound a cloath about his throat, ready to be put to the torture of water. Thus prepared, he prayed to be reſpited, and he would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs all. Being let down, he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain vowed and proteſted his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocencie; yet ſaid, that becauſe he knew that they would by tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture make him confeſs any thing, though never ſo falſe, they ſhould do him a great favour, to tell him what they would have him ſay, and he would ſpeak it, to avoid the torture. The Fiſcal hereupon ſaid; What, do you mock us? and bad, Up with him again; and ſo gave him the torment of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: which he not able long to endure, prayed to be let down again to his Confeſſion. Then he deviſed a little with himſelf, and told them, That about two moneths and a half before, him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, <hi>Tomſon, Johnſon, Brown,</hi> and <hi>Fardo,</hi> had plotted, with the help of the <hi>Japoners,</hi> to ſurpriſe the Caſtle. Here he was interrupted by the Fiſcal, and asked whether
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:169753:23"/>Captain <hi>Towerſon</hi> were not of that conſpiracie. He anſwered, No. You lie, ſaid the Fiſcal; did not he call you all to him, and tell you, that thoſe daily abuſes of the <hi>Dutch</hi> had cauſed him to think of a Plot, and that he wanted nothing but your conſent and ſecrecie? Then ſaid a Dutch Merchant, one <hi>John Jooſt</hi> that ſtood by. Did not you all ſwear upon a Bible to be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret to him? <hi>Collins</hi> anſwered with great Oaths, that he knew nothing of any ſuch matter. Then they bad make him faſt again: whereupon he then ſaid, All was true that they had ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken. Then the Fiſcal asked him, whether the Engliſh in the reſt of the Factories, were not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting to this Plot. He an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, No. The Fiſcal then asked him, whether the Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of the Engliſh at <hi>Jaccatra,</hi> or Maſter <hi>Welden</hi> A gent in <hi>Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da,</hi> were not Plotters or privy to this buſineſs. Again he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, No. Then the Fiſcal ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him, by what means the <hi>Iapo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners</hi> ſhould have executed their
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:169753:23"/>purpoſe. Whereat, when <hi>Collins</hi> ſtood ſtaggering and deviſing of ſome probable fiction, the Fiſcal holp him, and ſaid, Should not two <hi>Japoners</hi> have gone to each point of the Caſtle, and two to the Governours Chamber door; and when the hurly-burly had been without, and the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour coming to ſee what was the matter, the <hi>Japoners</hi> to have killed him? Here one that ſtood by, ſaid to the Fiſcal, Do not tell him what he ſhould ſay, but let him ſpeak of himſelf. Whereupon the Fiſcal, without attending the anſwer to his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer queſtion, asked what the <hi>Japoners</hi> ſhould have had for their reward. <hi>Collins</hi> anſwered, 1000 Ryals apiece. Laſtly, he asked him, when this plot ſhould have been effected. Whereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, although he anſwered him nothing (not knowing what to deviſe upon the ſudden) yet he was diſmiſſed, and very glad to come clear of the Torture, though with certain belief that he ſhould die for this his confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:169753:24"/>
                  <p>Next was <hi>Samuel Colſon</hi> brought in,
<note place="margin">Samuel Colſon <hi>examined.</hi>
                     </note> being newly arrived from <hi>Hitto,</hi> as is before touched, and was the ſame day brought to the Torture, who, for fear of the pain wherewith he ſaw <hi>Collins</hi> come out, in ſuch a caſe, that his eyes were almoſt blown out of his head with the Torment of water; choſe rather to confeſs all they asked him: and ſo was quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dismiſſed, coming out weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, lamenting, and proteſting his innocencie.</p>
                  <p>Then was <hi>John Clark,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">John Clark <hi>examined.</hi>
                     </note> that came with <hi>Colſon</hi> from <hi>Hitto,</hi> fetcht in, and a little after was heard (by the reſt that were with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out in the Hall) to crie out amain, They Tortured him with water and with fire, by the ſpace of two hours. The manner of his Torture (as alſo of <hi>Johnſons</hi> and <hi>Tomſons</hi>) was as followeth: Firſt they hoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him up by the hands with a cord on a large dore, where they made him faſt upon two ſtaples of Iron, fixt on both ſides at the top of the dore poſts, haling his hands one from the other as wide as they could ſtretch. Being thus
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:169753:24"/>made faſt, his feet hung ſome two foot from the ground; which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo they ſtretcht aſunder as far as they would retch, and ſo made them faſt beneath unto the dore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trees on each ſide. Then they bound a cloth about his neck and face ſo cloſe, that little or no water could go by. That done, they poured the water ſoftly up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his head untill the cloath was full up to the mouth and noſtrils, and ſomewhat higher; ſo that he could not draw breath, but he muſt withall ſuck in the water: which being ſtill continued to be poured in ſoftly, forced all his inward parts, came out of his noſe, ears, and eyes, and often, as it were ſtifling and choaking him, at length took away his breath, &amp; brought him to a ſwoun or faint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Then they took him quickly down, &amp; made him vomit up the water. Being a little recovered, they triced him up again, &amp; pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the water as before, eftſoons taking him down as he ſeemed to be ſtifled. In this manner they handled him three or four ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral times with water, till his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:169753:25"/>was ſwoln twice or thrice as big as before, his cheeks like great bladders, and his eyes ſtaring and ſtrutting out beyond his fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head: yet all this he bare, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out confeſſing any thing; inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as the Fiſcal and tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors reviled him, ſaying, that he was a Divel, and no man, or ſurely was a Witch, at leaſt had ſome charm about him, or was enchanted, that he could bear ſo much. Wherefore they cut off his hair very ſhort, as ſuppoſing he had ſome witchcraft hidden therein. Afterwards they hoiſed him up again as before, and then burnt him with lighted candles in the bottom of his feet, untill the fat dropt out the candles; yet then applied they freſh lights un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him. They burnt him alſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the elbows, and in the palms of the hands; likewiſe under the arm-pits, untill his inwards might evidently be ſeen. At laſt, when they ſaw he could of himſelf make no handſome confeſſion, then they led him along with queſtions of particular circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, by themſelves framed.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:169753:25"/>Being thus wearied and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come by the torment, he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, yea, to whatſoever they asked: whereby they drew from him a body of a confeſſion to this effect; to wit, That Captain <hi>Towerſon</hi> had upon New-years day laſt before, ſworn all the <hi>Engliſh</hi> at <hi>Amboyna</hi> to be ſecret and aſſiſtant to a plot that he had projected, with the help of the <hi>Japoners,</hi> to ſurpriſe the Caſtle, and to put the Governour and the reſt of the <hi>Dutch</hi> to death.</p>
                  <p>Having thus martyred this poor man, they ſent him out by four Blacks: who carried him between them to a dungeon, where he lay five or ſix dayes, without any Chirurgion to dreſs him, untill (his fleſh being putri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied) great Maggots dropt and crept fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him in a moſt loathſom and noiſom manner. Thus they fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed their Sabbath dayes work; &amp; it growing now dark, ſent the reſt of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> (that came that day from <hi>Hitto,</hi> &amp; till the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Hall) firſt to the Smith's ſhop, where they were loaden with Irons, and then to the ſame
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:169753:26"/>loathſome dungeon, where <hi>Clark</hi> and the reſt were, accompanied with the poor <hi>Iaponers,</hi> lying in the putrefaction of their tortures.</p>
                  <p>The next morning being Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day the ſeventeenth of February, old ſtile, <hi>William Griggs</hi> and <hi>Iohn Fardo,</hi> with certain <hi>Iaponers,</hi> were brought into the place of exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Iaponers</hi> were firſt cruelly tortured,
<note place="margin">William Griggs <hi>examined</hi>
                     </note> to accuſe <hi>Griggs,</hi> which at laſt they did: and <hi>Griggs,</hi> to avoid the like torture, confeſſed all that the Fiſcal demanded.
<note place="margin">Iohn Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do <hi>exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined.</hi>
                     </note> By and by the like alſo was done by <hi>Iohn Fardo,</hi> and other <hi>Iaponers:</hi> but <hi>Fardo</hi> himſelf endured the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of water, and at laſt confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed whatſoever the Fiſcal asked him; and ſo was ſent back to pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
                  <p>The ſame day alſo <hi>Iohn Beomont</hi> was brought the ſecond time to the Fiſcals chamber;
<note place="margin">Iohn Beo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mont <hi>exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined.</hi>
                     </note> where one Captain <hi>Newport</hi> a Dutch mans ſon (born in England) was uſed as an Interpreter. <hi>William Griggs</hi> was alſo brought in to accuſe him; who ſaid, that when the conſultation for taking of the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:169753:26"/>Caſtle, was held, then he (the ſaid <hi>Beomont</hi>) was preſent. <hi>Beomont</hi> denied it with great earneſtneſs and deep Oaths. At laſt being triced up, and drenched with water till his inwards were ready to crack, he anſwered affirmative<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to all the Fiſcals interrogato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries: yet as ſoon as he was let down, he clearly demonſtrated to Captain <hi>Newport,</hi> and <hi>Iohnſon</hi> a <hi>Dutch</hi> Merchant, then alſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, that theſe things could not be ſo. Nevertheleſs he was forced to put his hand to his confeſſion, or elſe he muſt to the torture a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, which to avoid, he ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed; and ſo had a great iron bolt and two ſhackles riveted to his legs, and then was carried back to priſon.</p>
                  <p>After this, <hi>George Sharrock,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">George Sharrock <hi>examined</hi>
                     </note> Aſſiſtant at <hi>Hitto,</hi> was called in queſtion; who, ſeeing how grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouſly others were martyred, made his earneſt prayer to God (as ſince upon his Oath he hath acknowledged) that he would ſuffer him to make ſome ſuch pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable lies againſt himſelf, as the <hi>Dutch</hi> might believe, and ſo he
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:169753:27"/>might eſcape the torment. Being brought to the Rack, the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter provided, and the candles lighted, he was by the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Fiſcal examined, and charged with the conſpiracie. He fell upon his knees, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted his innocencie. Then they commanded him to the Rack, and told him; Unleſs he would confeſs, he ſhould be torment<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with fire and water to death, and then ſhould be drawn by the heels to the gallows, and there hanged up. He ſtill perſiſting in this his innocencie, the Fiſcal bad him be hoiſed up. Then he craved reſpite a while, and told them, that he was at <hi>Hitto,</hi> and not in <hi>Amboyna,</hi> upon New-years day, when the conſulta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was pretended; neither had been there ſince <hi>November</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, as was well known to ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry of the <hi>Hollanders</hi> themſelves that reſided there alſo with him. Hereupon, they commanded him again to the Rack: but he, craving reſpite as before, now told them, that he had ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times heard <hi>Iohn Clark</hi> (who
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:169753:27"/>was with him at <hi>Hitto</hi>) ſay, That the <hi>Dutch</hi> had done them many unſufferable wrongs, and that he would be revenged of them: to which end, he had once broken with Captain <hi>Towerſon</hi> of a brave Plot. At which word the Fiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal and the reſt were attentive, encouraging him to proceed. So he went on, ſaying, that <hi>John Clark</hi> had intreated Captain <hi>Towerſon,</hi> that he might go to <hi>Maccaſſer,</hi> there to conſult and adviſe with the Spaniards to come with Gallies, and rob the ſmall Factories of <hi>Amboyna</hi> and <hi>Seran,</hi> when no ſhips were there. Here they asked him, what Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>Towerſon</hi> ſaid to this. He anſwered, that Captain <hi>Towerſon</hi> was very much offended with <hi>Clark</hi> for the motion; and from thenceforth could never abide him. Hereupon the Fiſcal cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led him Rogue, and ſaid he prated all from the matter, &amp; ſhould go to the torture. He craved favour again, and began another tale; to wit, that upon Twelf-day then laſt paſt, <hi>John Clark</hi> told him at <hi>Hitto,</hi> that there was a practiſe
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:169753:28"/>to take the Caſtle of <hi>Amboyna;</hi> and asked him, whether he would conſent thereunto. Whereupon he demanded of <hi>Clark,</hi> whether Captain <hi>Towerſon</hi> knew of any ſuch matter. Which, <hi>Clark</hi> affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming; then he (the ſaid <hi>Sharrock</hi>) ſaid, that he would do as the reſt did. Then the Fiſcal asked him, what time the conſultation was held. He anſwered, In <hi>Novem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> laſt. The <hi>Fiſcal</hi> ſaid, That could not be: for, the conſulta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was upon New-yerrs day. The Priſoner ſaid as before in the beginning; that he had not been in <hi>Amboyna</hi> ſince the firſt of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember, till now that he was brought thither. Why then, quoth the Fiſcal, have you belied your ſelf? whereto the Priſoner reſolutely anſwered, that all that he had ſpoken touching any trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, was falſe and feigned, onely to avoid torment. Then went the Fiſcal out into another room to the Governour, and anon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned, and ſent <hi>Sharrock</hi> unto the Priſon again. The next day he was called again, and a writing preſented him, wherein was
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:169753:28"/>framed a formal confeſſion of his laſt conference with <hi>Clark</hi> at <hi>Hitto,</hi> touching the plot to take the Caſtle of <hi>Amboyna:</hi> which being read over to him, the Fiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal asked him, whether it were true, or no. He anſwered, No, Why then, ſaid the Fiſcal, did you confeſs it? He anſwered, For fear of Torment. The Fiſcal and the reſt in a great rage told him he lied; his mouth had ſpoken it, and it was true, and therefore he ſhould ſubſcribe it. Which as ſoon as he had done, he fell pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently into a great paſſion charging them bitterly to be guiltie of the innocent bloud of himſelf and the reſt, which they ſhould look to anſwer for at the day of Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: withall he grappled with the Fiſcal, and would have ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped him from carrying in the confeſſion to the Governour, with whom he alſo craved to ſpeak; but was inſtantly laid hold on, and carried away to priſon.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>William Webber,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">William Webber <hi>examined.</hi>
                     </note> being next ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined, was told by the Fiſcal, that <hi>John Clark</hi> had confeſſed
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:169753:29"/>him to have been at <hi>Amboyna</hi> on New-years day, and ſworn to Captain <hi>Towerſon</hi>'s plot, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> All which he denied, alledging, he was that day at <hi>Larica:</hi> yet being brought to the torture, he then confeſſed, he had been at the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultation at <hi>Amboyna</hi> upon New-years day, with all the reſt of the circumſtances in order as he was asked. He alſo further told them, he had received a letter from <hi>Iohn Clark;</hi> after which was a Poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript, excuſing his brief writing at that time, for that there was great buſineſs in hand. But one <hi>Renier</hi> a Dutch Merchant, then ſtanding by, told the Governour, that upon New-years day, the time of this pretended conſulta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Webber</hi> and he were merrie at <hi>Larica.</hi> So the Governour left him, and went out. But the Fiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal held on upon the other point, touching the Poſtſcript of <hi>Clark</hi>'s Letter, urging him to ſhew the ſame. Which when he could not do, though often terrified with the torture, he gave him reſpite; promiſing to ſave his life, if he would produce that Letter.</p>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:169753:29"/>
                  <p>Then was Captain <hi>Towerſon</hi> brought to the examination,
<note place="margin">Gabriel Tower<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon <hi>exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined.</hi>
                     </note> and ſhewed what others had confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of him. He deeply proteſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his innocencie, <hi>Samuel Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> was brought to confront him: who being told, that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs he would now make good his former confeſſion againſt Captain <hi>Towerſon,</hi> he ſhould to the torture, coldly re-affirmed the ſame, and ſo was ſent away. They alſo brought <hi>William Grigs</hi> &amp; <hi>John Fardo</hi> to juſtifie their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer confeſſions to his face. Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>Towerſon</hi> ſeriouſly charged them, that as they would anſwer it at the dreadfull day of Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, they ſhould ſpeak nothing but the truth. Both of them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly fel down upon their knees before him; praying him for Gods ſake to forgive them, &amp; ſaying fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther openly before them all, that whatſoever they had formerly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, was moſt falſe, and ſpoken onely to avoid torment. With that the Fiſcal &amp; the reſt offered them again to the torture: which they would not endure, but then af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed their former confeſſions to be true.</p>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:169753:30"/>
                  <p>When <hi>Colſon</hi> (who had accuſed Captain <hi>Towerſon</hi> before) was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to ſet his hand to his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, he asked the Fiſcal, upon whoſe head he thought the ſin would lie; whether upon his that was conſtrained to confeſs what was falſe, or upon the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrainers. The Fiſcal, after a little pauſe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this queſtion, went in to the Governour then in another room; but anon returning, told <hi>Colſon</hi> he muſt ſubſcribe it: which he did; yet withall made this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation: Well, quoth he, you make me to accuſe my ſelf and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of that which is as falſe, as God is true: for, God is my wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs I am as innocent as the child new born.</p>
                  <p>Thus have they examined all that belong to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany in the ſeveral Factories of the Iſland of <hi>Amboyna.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The one and twentieth of February,
<note place="margin">John Wethe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral <hi>exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined.</hi>
                     </note> they examined <hi>John Wetheral,</hi> Factor at <hi>Cambello</hi> in the Iſland of <hi>Seran.</hi> He confeſſed, he was at <hi>Amboyna</hi> upon New-years day: but for the conſulta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, whereof he was demanded,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:169753:30"/>he ſaid he knew of no other but touching certain cloath of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Company, that lay in the Factories rotting and worm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaten, which they adviſed toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther how to put off to the beſt avail of their Imployers. The Governour ſaid, they queſtioned him not about cloath, but of treaſon: whereof when he had proteſted his innocencie, he was for that time dismiſſed. But the next day he was ſent for again, and Captain <hi>Towerſon</hi> brought to confront and accuſe him, having before (it ſeems) confeſſed ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what againſt him. But Mr. <hi>Tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erſon</hi> ſpake now theſe words onely: Oh, M. <hi>Wetheral,</hi> M. <hi>We<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theral,</hi> ſpeak the truth, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the truth, as God ſhall put into your heart. So Captain <hi>Towerſon</hi> was put out again, and <hi>Wetheral</hi> brought to the torture of water with great threats; if water would not make him con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, fire ſhould. He prayed them to tell him what he ſhould ſay, or to write down what they would, he would ſubſcribe it. They ſaid, he needed no Tutor;
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:169753:31"/>they would make him confeſs of himſelf. But when they had triced him up four ſeveral times, and ſaw he knew not what to ſay, then they read him other mens con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions, &amp; asked him from point to point, as they had done others: and he ſtill anſwered, Yea, to all.</p>
                  <p>Next was called in <hi>John Powl,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">John Powl <hi>exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Wetherals</hi> aſſiſtant at <hi>Camhello:</hi> but he, proving that he was not at <hi>Amboyna</hi> ſince November (ſave now when he was brought thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther priſoner) &amp; being ſpoken for by one <hi>Iohn Jooſt,</hi> who had long been well acquainted with him, was diſmiſſed without torture.</p>
                  <p>Then was <hi>Thomas Ladhrook,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Thomas Ladbrook <hi>examined.</hi>
                     </note> ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant to <hi>VVetheral</hi> &amp; <hi>Powl</hi> at <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hello,</hi> brought to be examined: but proving that he was at <hi>Cambello</hi> at the time of the pretended con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultation, and ſerving in ſuch qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, as that he was never acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with any of the Letters from the Agent of <hi>Amboyna,</hi> he was eaſily and quickly diſmiſſed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ephraim Ramſey</hi> was alſo exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined upon the whole pretended conſpiracie,
<note place="margin">Ephraim Ramſey <hi>examined.</hi>
                     </note> and particularly que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtioned co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning Captain <hi>VVel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi>
                     <pb n="30" facs="tcp:169753:31"/>the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Agent in <hi>Banda,</hi> but denying all, and proving that he was not at <hi>Amboyna</hi> at New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>years tide, being alſo ſpoken for by <hi>Iohn Iooſt;</hi> was diſmiſſed, after he had hanged in the Rack a good while, with irons upon his legs, and the cloath about his mouth.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, <hi>Iohn-Sadler,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">John Sadler <hi>examined.</hi>
                     </note> ſervant to <hi>William Grigs</hi> at <hi>Larica,</hi> was exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined; and being found to have been abſent from <hi>Amboyna</hi> at New-years tide, when <hi>Grigs</hi> and others were there, was diſmiſſed.</p>
                  <p>Thus have we all their exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations tortures, and confeſſions, being the work of 8. days, from the 15. to the 23. of <hi>February.</hi> After which, was two dayes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpite before the ſentence. <hi>John Powl,</hi> being himſelf acquitted as before ſaid, went to the priſon to viſit <hi>John Fardo,</hi> one of thoſe that had accuſed Captain <hi>Tower<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</hi> To him <hi>Fardo</hi> religiouſly proteſted his innocencie; but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially his ſorrow for accuſing Maſter <hi>Towerſon:</hi> for, ſaid he, the fear of death doth nothing diſmay me; for, God (I truſt) will be mercifull to my ſoul,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:169753:32"/>according to the innocencie of my cauſe. The onely matter that troubleth me, is, that through fear of Torment I have accuſed that honeſt and godly man Captain <hi>Towerſon,</hi> who (I think in my conſcience) was ſo upright and honeſt towards all men, that he harboured no ill will to any, much leſs would attempt any ſuch bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs as he is accuſed of. He fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſaid, he would before his death receive the Sacrament, in acknowledgement that he had ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed Captain <hi>Towerſon</hi> falſly and wrongfully, onely through fear of Torment.</p>
                  <p>The five and twentieth of <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bruary,</hi> old ſtile, all the priſoners, as well the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> as the <hi>Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal</hi> and the <hi>Iaponers,</hi> were brought into the great Hall of the Caſtle, and there were ſolemnly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, except <hi>Iohn Powel, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraim Ramſey, Iohn Sadler,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Ladbrook,</hi> formerly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitted, as aforeſaid.</p>
                  <p>Captain <hi>Towerſon</hi> having been (during all his impriſonment) kept apart from the reſt, ſo that none of them could come to
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:169753:32"/>ſpeak with him; writ much in his Chamber (as ſome of the Dutch report,) but all was ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, ſave onely a Bill of debt, which one <hi>Th. Iohnſon,</hi> a free Burgher got of him by favour of his keepers for acknowledgement, that the Engliſh Company owed him a certain ſum of mony. In the end of this Bill he writ theſe words: <hi>Firmed by the Firm of me</hi> Gabriel Towerſon <hi>now appointed to die guiltles of any thing that can be juſtly laid to my charge. God forgive them their guilt; and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive me to his mercie. Amen.</hi> This Bill being brought to M. <hi>Welden</hi> the Engliſh Agent at Banda, he paid the money, and received in the acknowledgement.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>VVilliam Griggs</hi> (who had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore accuſed Captain <hi>Towerſon</hi>) writ theſe words following in his Table-book: <hi>VVe, whoſe names are here ſpecified;</hi> John Beomont, <hi>Merchant of</hi> Loho, William Griggs <hi>Merchant of Larica,</hi> Abel Price, <hi>Chirurgian of</hi> Amboyna. Robert Brown, <hi>Tailor, which do here lie Priſoners in the Ship</hi> Rotterdam, <hi>being apprehended
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:169753:33"/>for conſpiracie, for blowing up the Caſtle of</hi> Amboyna: <hi>we being judged to death this fifth of March.</hi> Anno 1622. <hi>which we through torment were conſtrained to ſpeak, that which we never meant, nor once imagined; the which we take upon our deaths and ſalvation: they tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured us with that extream torment of fire and water, that fleſh and bloud could not endure: and this we take upon our deaths, that they have put us to death guiltleſs of our ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation. So therefore we deſire, that they that ſhall underſtand this; that our Imployers may underſtand theſe wrongs, and that your ſelves would have a care to look to your ſelves: for their intent was to have brought you in alſo; they askt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning you; which if they had tortured us, we muſt have confeſſed you alſo. And ſo farewel; written in the dark.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This Table-book was after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards delivered to M. <hi>Welden</hi> afore-named by one that ſerved the Dutch</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Samuel Colſon</hi> alſo, another that accuſed Captain <hi>Towerſon,</hi> writ as followeth in the waſte leaves of a book, wherein were bound toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:169753:33"/>the Common-Prayers, the Pſalms, and the Catechiſm.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In one page thus;</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <p>March 5. <hi>Stilo novo,</hi> being Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, aboard the <hi>Rotterdam,</hi> ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Irons:</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>UNderſtand that I</hi> Samuel Colſon, <hi>late Factour of</hi> Hitto, <hi>was apprehended for ſuspicion of conspiracie; and for any thing I know, muſt die for it: wherefore, having no better means to make my innocencie known, have writ this in this book, hoping ſome good</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh <hi>men will ſee it. I do here upon my ſalvation, as I hope by his death and paſsion to have redemption for my ſins, that I am clear of all ſuch conspiracie; neither do I know any Engliſh man guilty thereof; nor o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther creature in the World. As this is true: God bleſs me.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Sam. Colſon.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>On the other ſide, upon the firſt page of the Chatechiſm, is thus written:</p>
                  <q>
                     <p>
                        <hi>IN another leaf you ſhall under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand more, which I have written in this book.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Sam. Colſon.</p>
                  </q>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:169753:34"/>
                  <p>In the beginning of the Pſalms and in the leaf ſo referred unto, is thus written, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <p>
                        <hi>THe Iapons were taken with ſome villany, and brought to examination: being moſt tyrannouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tortured, were asked if the</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh <hi>had any hand in the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> 
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>lot. VVhich torture made them ſay, Yea. Then was Master</hi> Tomſon, <hi>M.</hi> Johnſon, <hi>M.</hi> Collins, John Clark <hi>brought to examination, and were burned under the arms, arm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pits, the hands, and ſoals of the feet, with another moſt miſerable tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to drink water; ſome of them almoſt tortured to death, and were forced to confeſs that which they never knew, by reaſon of the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which fleſh and bloud is not able to endure. Then were the reſt of the Engliſh men called one by one (amongſt which I was one) being wiſhed to confeſs, or elſe I muſt go to torment; withall cauſed M.</hi> Johnſon, <hi>who was before tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented, to witneſs againſt me, or elſe be ſhould be tormented again; which rather than he would endure, he ſaid, VVhat they would have, be
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:169753:34"/>would speak. Then muſt I confeſs that I never knew, or elſe to go to torment; which rather than I would ſuffer, I did confeſs that, which (as I ſhall he ſaved before God Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie) is not true, being forced for fear of torment. Then did they make us witneſſe againſt Captain</hi> Towerſon, <hi>and at laſt made Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain</hi> Towerſon <hi>confeſs all, being for fear of moſt cruel torment; for which we muſt all die. As I mean and hope to have pardon for my ſins, I know no more than the child unborn of this buſineſs. VVritten with my own hand the firſt of March,</hi> Stilo novo.</p>
                     <p>Sam. Colſon.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>Yet in another page were theſe words:</p>
                  <q>
                     <p>I <hi>VVas born in New-Caſtle upon</hi> Tyne, <hi>where I deſire this book may come, that my friends may know of my innocencie.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Sam. Colſon.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>This book he delivered to one that ſerved the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> who ſowed it up in his bed, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, at his opportunity deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it to M. <hi>VVelden</hi> before named</p>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:169753:35"/>
                  <p>All theſe ſaid writings are yet extant under the hands of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral parties, well known to their friends here in <hi>England.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſix and twentieth of Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bruary, <hi>Stilo veteri,</hi> the Priſoners were all brought into the great Hall of the Caſtle (except Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>Towerſon</hi> &amp; <hi>Emanuel Tom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi>) to be prepared for death by the miniſters. The <hi>Iaponeers</hi> now all in general, as ſome of them had done before in particular, cryed out unto the Engliſh, ſaying; Oh you Engliſh men, where did we ever in our lives eat with you, talk with you, or (to our remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance) ſee you? The Engliſh an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, Why then have you ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed us? The poor men, percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving they were made believe each had accuſed others, before they had ſo done indeed; ſhewed them their tortur'd bodies, and ſaid, If a ſtone were thus burnt, would it not change his nature? how much more we that are fleſh and bloud?</p>
                  <p>Whil'ſt they were all in the Hall, Cap. <hi>Towerſon</hi> was brought up into the place of examination and two great Jarres of water carried
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:169753:35"/>after him. What he there did or ſuffered was unknown to the Engliſh without: but it ſeemeth they made him then to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>write his confeſſion. After ſupper <hi>John Powl, Ephraim Ramſey, Th. Ladbrook,</hi> and <hi>Iohn Sadler,</hi> who were found not guily, as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, were taken from the reſt, and put into another room. By and by alſo were <hi>Samuel Colſon,</hi> and <hi>Edward Collins</hi> brought from the reſt; into the room where <hi>Ema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuel Tomſon</hi> lay: The Fiſcal told them, it was the Governours mercie, to ſave one of them three: and it being indifferent to him, which of them were the man, it was his pleaſure they ſhould draw lots for it, which they did, and the free lot fell to <hi>Edward Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lins;</hi> who then was carried away to the Chamber, where <hi>John Powl</hi> and the reſt that were quit, lodged, and <hi>Samuel Colſon</hi> back into the Hall. Anon alſo <hi>John Beomont</hi> was brought out of the Hall into the Chamber, where <hi>John Powl,</hi> and the reſt of the acquitted perſons were, and was told, that he was beholding to
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:169753:36"/>
                     <hi>Peter Iohnſon</hi> the Dutch Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant of <hi>Lobo,</hi> and to the Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie; for they two had begged his life.</p>
                  <p>So then there remained in the Hall ten of the Engliſh; for Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>Towerſon</hi> &amp; <hi>Emmanuel Tom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> (as is ſaid before) were kept in ſeveral rooms apart from the reſt. To theſe that remained in the Hall, came the Dutch Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, who telling them how ſhort a time they had to live, admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed and exhorted them to make their true confeſſions; for it was a dangerous and deſperate thing, to diſſemble at ſuch a time. The Engliſh ſtill profeſſed their innocencie, and prayed the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters that they might all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Sacraments, as a ſeal of the forgiveneſs of their ſins; and withall, thereby to confirm their laſt profeſſion of their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocencie. But this would by no means be granted. Whereupon <hi>Samuel Colſon</hi> ſaid thus unto the Miniſters; You manifeſt unto us the danger of diſſimulation in this caſe. But tell us, if we ſuffer guiltleſs, being other wiſe alſo true
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:169753:36"/>believers in Chriſt Jeſus, What ſhall be our reward? The Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher anſwered, By how much the clearer you are, ſo much the more glorious ſhal be your reſurrection. With that word, <hi>Colſon</hi> ſtarted up, imbraced the Preacher, &amp; gave him his purſe,, with ſuch money as he had in it, ſaying; <hi>Domine,</hi> God bleſs you: tell the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, I freely forgive him; and I intreat you, to exhort him to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent him of his bloudy tragedy, wrought upon us poor innocent ſouls. Here all the reſt of the Engliſh ſignified their conſent to this Speech. Then ſpake <hi>John Fardo</hi> to the reſt, in preſence of the Miniſters, as followeth: My Countrey-men, and Brethren, all that are here with me co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demned to die, I charge you all, as you will anſwer it at Gods judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſeat, if any of you be guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of this matter, whereof we are condemned, diſcharge your conſciences, and confeſs the truth for ſatisfaction of the World. Hereupon <hi>Samuel Colſon</hi> ſpake with a loud voice, ſaying, Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to my innocencie in this
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:169753:37"/>treaſon, ſo Lord pardon all the reſt of my ſins: and if I be guilty thereof more or leſs, let me ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be partaker of thy heavenly joyes. At which words every one of the reſt cried out, Amen for me, Amen for me, good Lord. This done, each of them know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing whom he had accuſed, went one to another begging forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes for their falſe accuſation, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wrung from them by the pains or fear of torture. And they all freely forgave one another: for none had been ſo falſly accuſed, but he himſelf had accuſed ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as falſly. In particular, <hi>George Sharrock</hi> (who ſurvived to relate this nights paſſage) kneeled down to <hi>Iohn Clark,</hi> whom he had ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed of the tale at <hi>Hitto</hi> above mentioned, and craved forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs at his hands. <hi>Clark</hi> freely forgave him, ſaying; how ſhould I look to be forgiven of God, if I ſhould not forgive you, having my ſelf ſo falſly accuſed Captain <hi>Towerſon,</hi> and others?</p>
                  <p>After this, they ſpent the reſt of the dolefull night in Prayer, ſinging of Pſalms, and comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:169753:37"/>one another; though the Dutch that guarded them, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered them wine, bidding them drink <hi>Luſtick,</hi> and drive away the ſorrow; according to the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom of their own Nation in the like caſe, but contrarie to the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Engliſh.</p>
                  <p>Upon the morrow morning, being the execution day, the 27. of February, <hi>Stilo veteri, John Powl</hi> being freed (as is above re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited) came into the room where the condemned perſons were, and found them at Prayer. They all requeſted him to relate unto their friends in England, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocencie of their cauſe; taking it upon their deaths, that what they had co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſed againſt themſelves &amp; others touching this crime, was all falſe, &amp; forced by fear of torture.</p>
                  <p>The ſame morning <hi>William Wehber</hi> was called again into the Fiſcals room, and there preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to produce the letter, which he had before confeſſed to have received from <hi>John Clark,</hi> in the <hi>Poſtſcript</hi> whereof ſome great bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs was intimated. They pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed him his life, if he would
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:169753:38"/>deliver or produce them that let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: which although he did not, nor indeed could, yet at laſt they pardoned him, and ſent him to the reſt that were ſaved, and <hi>Sharrock</hi> with him.</p>
                  <p>That morning <hi>Emanuel Tomſon</hi> underſtanding that <hi>John Beomont</hi> was pardoned, made means to have him come and ſpeak with him; which, with much ado, he obtained. <hi>Beomont</hi> found him ſitting in a Chamber, all alone in a moſt miſerable faſhion; the wounds of his torture bound up, but the matter &amp; gore-bloud iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing through the Rollers. He took M. <hi>Beomont</hi> by the hand, and prayed him, when he came into England, to do his duty to the Honourable Company, his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, to M. <hi>Robinſon,</hi> and to his brother <hi>Billingſley,</hi> and to certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie them of his innocencie, which (ſaid he) you your ſelf know well enough.</p>
                  <p>All things being prepared for the execution, the condemned were brought forth of the Hall along by the Chamber where the quit and pardoned were; who
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:169753:38"/>ſtood in the dore, to give and take the farewell of their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey-men now going to execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Staying a little for this purpoſe, they prayed and charged thoſe, that were ſaved, to bear witneſs to their friends in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land of their innocencie, and that they died not Traitors, but ſo many Innocents, meerly mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered by the Hollanders, whom they prayed God to forgive their bloud-thirſtineſs, and to have mercie upon their own ſouls.</p>
                  <p>Being brought into the Yard, their ſentence was there read unto them from a Gallery, and then they were thence carried unto the place of execution, together with nine <hi>Japons</hi> and a Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal: not the ordinarie and ſhort way, but round about in a long proceſſion, through the Town; the way guarded with five Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of Souldiers, Dutch, and Amboyners, and thronged with the Natives of the Iſland, that (upon the ſummons given the day before by the ſound of the Drum) flocked together to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold this triumph of the Dutch
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:169753:39"/>over the Engliſh. <hi>Samuel Colſon</hi> had conceived a Prayer in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, in the end whereof he prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted his innocencie: which Prayer he read to his fellows the night before, and now alſo at the place of execution devoutly pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the ſame; then threw away the paper, which the Governour cauſed to be brought to him, and kept it,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Emanuel Tomſon</hi> told the reſt, he did not doubt but GOD would ſhew ſome ſign of their innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; and every one of the reſt took it ſeverally upon their death, that they were utterly guiltleſs; and ſo one by one with great cheerful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſuffered the fatal ſtroke.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Portugal</hi> prayed over his Beads very devoutly, and often kiſſed the Croſs; ſwearing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, that he was utterly innocent of this treaſon: yet confeſſed, that God had juſtly brought this pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment upon him, for that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a wife in his own Countrey, he had, by the perſwaſion of the Dutch Governour, taken another in that Countrey, his firſt being yet living.</p>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:169753:39"/>
                  <p>The <hi>Japons</hi> likewiſe (accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their Religion) ſhut up their laſt Act with the like profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of their innocencie. So there ſuffered ten Engliſh men, <hi>viz.</hi> Captain <hi>Gabriel Towerſon</hi> the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent of the Engliſh at <hi>Amboyna, Samuel Colſon</hi> Factor at <hi>Hitto, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manuel Tomſon</hi> Aſſiſtant at <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boyna, Timothy Johnſon</hi> Aſſiſtant there alſo, <hi>John Wetheral</hi> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor at <hi>Cambello, John Clark</hi> Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtant at <hi>Hitto, William Griggs</hi> Factor at <hi>Larica, John Fardo</hi> Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of the houſe, <hi>Ahel Price</hi> Chirurgian, and <hi>Robert Brown</hi> Tailor.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Portugal</hi> alſo ſuffered with them. His name was <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin Perez.</hi> He was born at <hi>Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gala.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The names of the <hi>Japoneſes</hi> that ſuffered (if any be curious to know them) were as follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth:
<list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Hititſo,</hi> all born at <hi>Firando.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Tſioſa,</hi> all born at <hi>Firando.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Sinſa.</hi> all born at <hi>Firando.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Sidney Migiel,</hi> born at <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganſacque.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Pedro Congie,</hi> born at <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganſacque.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Thome Corea.</hi> born at <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganſacque.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <pb n="48" facs="tcp:169753:40"/>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Quiandayo</hi> native of Coraets.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Tſabinda</hi> of Tſoncketgo.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Zanchoe</hi> of Fiſien.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>Beſides theſe, there were two o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Japoneſes;</hi> the one named <hi>Soyſimo,</hi> born at <hi>Firando;</hi> and the other <hi>Sacoube,</hi> of the ſame place: the former of which being tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured, confeſſed both to have been privy to this pretended trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and to have offered his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice unto the Engliſh to aid them in taking of the Caſtle: and the latter confeſſed to have had knowledge of the conſultation of the other <hi>Japons</hi> to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. But neither of them was executed, nor ſo much as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned. The reaſon whereof was not known to the Engliſh that were ſaved.</p>
                  <p>They had prepared a cloath of black Velvet, for Captain <hi>Tower<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi>'s body to fall upon; which being ſtained and defaced with his bloud, they afterwards put to the account of the Engliſh Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany.</p>
                  <p>At the inſtant of the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, there aroſe a great dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:169753:40"/>with a ſudden and violent guſt of wind and tempeſt; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by two of the Dutch ſhips, riding in the harbour, were driven from their Anchors, and with great labour and defficulty ſaved from the Rocks. Within a few dayes after, one <hi>William Dunckin,</hi> who had told the Governour. That <hi>Robert Brown,</hi> the Engliſh Tai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, had a few Moneths before told him, he hoped, that within ſix Moneths the Engliſh ſhould have as much to do in the Caſtle of <hi>Amboyna,</hi> as the Dutch: This fellow, coming upon an evening to the grave where the Engliſh were buried, being all (ſave Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>Towerſon</hi>) in one pit, fell down upon the grave; and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving lien there a while, roſe up again ſtark mad, and ſo conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued two or three dayes toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and then died. Forthwith alſo fell a new ſickneſs at <hi>Amboy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> which ſwept away about a thouſand people Dutch and <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boyners:</hi> in the ſpace wherein, there uſually died not above thirty at other ſeaſons. Theſe ſigns were by the ſurviuing Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:169753:41"/>referred to the confident pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction of <hi>Emanuel Tomſon</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>above-named, and were by the <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boyners</hi> interpreted as a token of the wrath of God for this barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Tyranny of the Hollanders.</p>
                  <p>The next day after the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, being the eight and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth of February, <hi>Stilo veteri,</hi> was ſpent in Triumph for the new General of the Dutch then pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed, and in publick rejoycing for the deliverance from this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended treaſon. The day follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, being the firſt of March, <hi>Iohn Beomont, George Sharrock, Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Collins,</hi> and <hi>William Webber,</hi> were brought to the Governour; who told <hi>Webber Beomont</hi> and <hi>Sharrock,</hi> that they were par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned in Honour of the new Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral; and <hi>Collins,</hi> that he was to go to <hi>Jaccatra,</hi> there to ſtand to the favour of the General. So the Governour made them drink wine with him, and curteouſly diſmiſſed them: willing them to go and conſult with the reſt that were ſaved, who were fit to be placed in the ſeveral Factories. Which done, and their opinions
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:169753:41"/>reported to the Governour, he accordingly commanded each to his place; adding, that he would thenceforth take upon him the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage and Government of the Engliſh Companies buſineſs. To which purpoſe, he had within a few dayes paſt opened a Letter that came from the Engliſh Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident at <hi>Iaccatra,</hi> directed to Captain <hi>Towerſon;</hi> being (as he ſaid) the firſt Engliſh Letter that ever he intercepted; further, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that he was glad that he ſound by that Letter, that the Engliſh at <hi>Iaccatra</hi> were innocent touching this buſineſs.</p>
                  <p>The Governour and Fiſcal ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving thus made an end at <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boyna,</hi> diſpatched themſelves for <hi>Banda:</hi> where they made very di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent enquiry againſt Captain <hi>Welden,</hi> the Engliſh Agent there; yet found no colour nor ſhadow of guilt to lay hold on: but at laſt entertained him with courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſpeeches, profeſſing to be very glad, that they found him, as well as the Engliſh at <hi>Iacca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra,</hi> to be without ſuſpition of this Treaſon (as they tearm it.)
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:169753:42"/>Captain <hi>VVelden,</hi> perceiving the diſorder and confuſion of the Engliſh Companies affairs at <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boyna,</hi> by means of this dealing of the <hi>Dutch;</hi> forthwith hired a <hi>Dutch Pinnace</hi> at <hi>Banda,</hi> and paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to <hi>Amboyna:</hi> where, inſtantly upon his arrival, he re-called the Companies ſervants, ſent (as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) by the <hi>Dutch</hi> Governour to the upper-factories.</p>
                  <p>Having enquired of them, and the reſt that were left at <hi>Amboy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> of the whole proceedings lately paſſed, he found, by the conſtant and agreeing relation of them all, that there was no ſuch Treaſon of the Engliſh as was pretended: as alſo underſtanding what ſtrict command the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour had given to the ſurviving Engliſh, not once to talk or confer with the Countrey peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple concerning this bloudy buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, although the ſaid Countrey people every day reproched them with treaſon, and a bloudy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention to have maſſacred the Natives, and to have ripped up the bellies of women with child, and ſuch like ſtuff; wherewith
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:169753:42"/>the Dutch have poſſeſſed the poor Vulgar, to make the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh odious unto them. The ſaid M. <hi>VVelden</hi> therefore finding it to ſort neither with the Honour nor profit of the Engliſh Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, his Maſters, to hold any longer reſidence in <hi>Amboyna,</hi> he took the poor remnant of the Engliſh along with him, in the ſaid hired <hi>Pinnace</hi> for <hi>Iaccatra;</hi> whither the Governour had ſent <hi>Iohn Beomont</hi> and <hi>Edward Collins</hi> before, as men condemned, and left to the mercie of the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral.</p>
                  <p>When this heavy news of <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boyna</hi> came to <hi>Iaccatra</hi> and the Engliſh there, the Preſident forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with ſent to the General of the Dutch, to know by what Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority the Governour of <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boyna</hi> had thus proceeded againſt the Engliſh, and how he and the reſt of the Dutch there at <hi>Iac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catra,</hi> did approve theſe proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings. The Governour returned for anſwer, that, The Governour of <hi>Amboyna</hi>'s Authority was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived from that of the Lords States General of the United
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:169753:43"/>Neatherlands; under whom he had lawfull Juriſdiction both in Criminal and civil cauſes, within the deſtrict of <hi>Amboyna;</hi> further, that ſuch proceeding was neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary againſt Traitours, ſuch as the Engliſh executed at <hi>Amboyna,</hi> might appear to be by their own confeſſions: a Copy whereof he therewith ſent to the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Preſident; who ſent the ſame back to be Authentickly certifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but received it not again.</p>
                  <p>Hitherto hath been recited the bare and naked Narration of the Progreſs and paſſage of this acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as it is taken out of the Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions of ſix ſeveral Engliſh Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors; whereof four were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, and the other two ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitted in this Proceſs of <hi>Amboy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na:</hi> all, ſince their return into England, examined upon their Oaths in the Admiralty Court. The particular of Captain <hi>Tower<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi>'s, as alſo of <hi>Emanuel Tomſon</hi>'s examinations and anſwers, are not yet come to light, by reaſon that theſe two were kept apart from all the reſt, and each alone by himſelf; nor any other of the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:169753:43"/>Engliſh ſuffered to come to ſpeak with them, except onely that ſhort Farewell, which <hi>Iohn Beomont</hi> took of <hi>Tomſon</hi> the morning before the execution be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mentioned. The like obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity is yet touching the examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and anſwers of diverſe of the reſt that are executed; being, during their impriſonment, ſo ſtrictly lookt to, and watched by the Dutch, that they might not talk together, nor mutually re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late their miſeries.</p>
                  <p>But becauſe the Hollanders defend their own proceedings by the confeſſions of the parties exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted, acknowledging ſeverally under their hands, that they were guilty of the pretended crime; it will not be amiſs to recollect and recall unto this place, as it were unto one ſum and totall, certain circumſtances diſperſed in ſeveral parts of this Narration; whereby, as well the innocencie of the Engliſh, as the unlawfull proceedings againſt them, may be manifeſted.</p>
                  <p>Firſt therefore it is to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred, that the <hi>Japons</hi> were
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:169753:44"/>apprehended, examined, and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured three or four dayes, before the <hi>Engliſh</hi> were attached; and the fame as well of their appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion, as torture, was rife and notorious in the Town of <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boyna,</hi> and the parts adjoyning. <hi>Tomſon,</hi> in this <hi>interim,</hi> and the very firſt day of the examination of the <hi>Japon,</hi> went to the Caſtle to ask leave of the Governour to land ſome Rice, and brought back the news with him to the Engliſh houſe of the cruel hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of theſe poor <hi>Iapons.</hi> This had been <hi>Item</hi> enough to the Engliſh, if they had been guilty, to ſhift for themſelves: whereto alſo they had ready means by the Curricurries or ſmall Boats of the <hi>Amboyners,</hi> which lie along the Strand in great number, wherewith they might eaſily have tranſported themſelves to <hi>Seran,</hi> to <hi>Bottoom,</hi> or to <hi>Maccaſſar,</hi> out of the reach and Juriſdiction of the Dutch; but in that they fled not in this caſe, it is a very ſtrong preſumption, that they were as little privy to any trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of their own, as ſuſpicious of
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:169753:44"/>any treachcerous tran laid for their blouds.</p>
                  <p>In the next place let it be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, how impoſſible it was for the Engliſh to atchieve this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended enterpriſe.</p>
                  <p>The Caſtle of <hi>Amboyna</hi> is of a very great ſtrength (as is before declared;) the Garriſon therein two or three hundred men, beſides as many more of their free Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers in the Town. What their care and circumſpection in all their Forts is, may appear, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the quick Alarm they now took at the fooliſh queſtion of the poor <hi>Japon,</hi> made to the Sentinel above-recited; but alſo by that which a little before happened at <hi>Jaccatra,</hi> where one of their Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers was ſhot to death for ſleep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the watch.</p>
                  <p>Durſt ten Engliſh men (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of not one a Souldier) attempt any thing upon ſuch a ſtrength and vigilancie? As for the aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the <hi>Japons,</hi> they were but ten neither, and all un-armed as well as the Engliſh: For, as at the ſeizure of the Engliſh houſe, all the proviſion therein found
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:169753:45"/>was but three ſwords, two Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets, and half a pound of powder: ſo the <hi>Japons</hi> (except when they are in ſervice of the Caſtle, and there armed by the <hi>Dutch</hi>) are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed to have no Arms, but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a <hi>Catan,</hi> a kind of ſhort ſword: and it is forbidden to all the <hi>Dutch,</hi> upon great penaltie, to ſell any hand-gun, powder or bullets to the <hi>Japons</hi> or <hi>Amboyners.</hi> But let it be imagined, that theſe 20 perſons <hi>Engliſh &amp; Japons,</hi> were ſo deſperate as to adventure the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploit; how ſhould they be able to maſter the <hi>Dutch</hi> in the Caſtle, or to keep poſſeſſion when they had gotten it? what ſecond had they? There was neither Ship nor Pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> in the harbor. All the reſt of the <hi>Japons</hi> in the Iſland, were not twenty perſons, and not one <hi>Engliſh</hi> more. The neareſt of the reſt of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> were at <hi>Banda,</hi> forty leagues from <hi>Amboyna;</hi> and thoſe but nine per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, all afterwards cleared by the Governour and <hi>Fiſcal</hi> themſelves from all ſuſpition of this pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed crime, as were alſo the reſt of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> at <hi>Jaccatra.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:169753:45"/>
                  <p>On the other ſide, beſides the ſtrength of the Caſtle and Town of <hi>Amboyna,</hi> the <hi>Hollanders</hi> have three other ſtrong Caſtles, well furniſhed with Souldiers in the ſame Iſland, and at <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bello</hi> near adjoyning. They had then alſo in the road of <hi>Amboy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi> eight Ships and Veſſels, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the <hi>Rotterdam</hi> of 1200 Tun, the <hi>Unicorn</hi> of 300 Tun, the Free-mans Veſſel of 100 Tun, the <hi>Calck</hi> of 60 Tun, Captain <hi>Gamals Junck</hi> of 40 Tun, the <hi>Flute</hi> of 300 Tun, the <hi>Amſterdam</hi> of 1400 Tun, and a ſmall Pinnace of about 60 Tun; and all theſe well furniſhed with men and Ammunition. It is true, that the Stories do record ſundry valiant and hardy enterpriſes of the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> Nation, and <hi>Holland</hi> is wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of ſome of them, yea, hath reaped the fruit of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> reſolution; yet no Storie, no Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gend ſcarcely reporteth any ſuch hardineſs, either of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> or others, That ſo few perſons, ſo naked of all proviſions &amp; ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies, ſhould undertake ſuch an adventure upon a counter-party,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:169753:46"/>ſo well and abundantly fitted at all points.</p>
                  <p>But let it be further granted, that they might poſſibly have overcome all theſe difficulties; yet to what end and purpoſe ſhould they put themſelves into ſuch a jeopardie? They knew well enough, that it was agreed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween both companies at home, That the Forts in the <hi>Indies</hi> ſhould remain reſpectively in the hands of ſuch, as had poſſeſſion of them at the date of the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, <hi>Anno</hi> 1619. and that the ſame was ratified by the Kings Majeſtie, and the Lords States General. They knew likewiſe, and all the world takes know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of his Majeſties Religious obſervation of Peace and Treatie with all his neighbours, yea, with all the world: what reward then could theſe Engliſh hope for, of this their Valour and danger? Certainly none other than that which is expreſly provided by the Treaty it ſelf, that is, To be puniſhed as the diſturbers of the Common Peace, and Amity of both Nations.</p>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:169753:46"/>
                  <p>But let theſe <hi>Engliſh</hi> men have been as fooliſh in this plot as the <hi>Hollanders</hi> will have them; is it alſo to be imagined, that they were ſo graceleſs, as when they were condemned, and ſeriouſly admoniſhed by the Miniſters to diſcharge their conſciences, yet then to perſiſt in their diſſimula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, being otherwiſe of ſuch godly behaviour, as to ſpend the time in Prayer ſinging of Pſalms; and ſpiritual comforting one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, which the <hi>Dutch</hi> would have had them beſtow in drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to drive away their ſorrow? Let <hi>Colſons</hi> queſtion to the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter be conſidered: his and the reſts offer and deſire to receive the Sacrament, in ſign and token of their innocencie; their mutual asking forgiveneſs for their like falſe accuſations of one another, forced by the Torture; <hi>Tomſons</hi> laſt farewell to <hi>Beomont; Colſons</hi> prayer, and his writing in his Prayer book; <hi>Fardo</hi>'s farewell to <hi>Powel;</hi> alſo his conjuring exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to his fellows, to diſcharge their conſciences, and all their anſwers thereunto; craving Gods
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:169753:47"/>mercie or judgement, according to their innocencie in this cauſe; their general and Religious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of their innocencie, to their Countrey men, at their laſt parting with them, and finally, the ſealing of this profeſſion with their laſt breath and bloud, even in the very Article of death, and in the ſtroke of the Executio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. What horrible and unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ampled diſſimulation were this? If ſome one or more of them had been ſo fearfully deſperate, yet would not there one amongſt ten be found to think of the judgement to come; whereunto he was then inſtantly ſummoned without Eſſoin, Bail, or Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe? What? had they hope of reprieve and life, if they kept their countenance to the laſt? Yet what hope had <hi>Tomſom</hi> and the reſt, when Captain <hi>Towerſon</hi>'s head was off? Nay, what deſire had <hi>Tomſon</hi> and <hi>Clark</hi> to live, being ſo mangled and martyred by the Torture? They were exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted one by one, and every one ſeveral took it upon his death, that he was guiltleſs.</p>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:169753:47"/>
                  <p>Now to blanch and ſmooth over all this rough and Barbarous proceeding; it is here given out, that the Governour and Fiſcal found ſuch evidence of the plot, and dealt ſo evenly in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, that they ſpared not their own people; having uſed ſome of their Native <hi>Hollanders,</hi> partakers of this treaſon, in the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as they did the <hi>Engliſh.</hi> But this, as well by the Relation here truely and faithfully ſet down, grounded upon the ſworn Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonie of ſix credible witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, as alſo by other ſufficient re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports of diverſe (lately come out of thoſe parts) appeareth to be a meer tale, not once alledged by any in the <hi>Indies</hi> in many moneths after the execution, but onely invented and diſperſed here, for a <hi>Fucus</hi> and a fair colour up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the whole cauſe, and to make the world believe, that the ground of this Barbarous and Tyrannous proceeding was a true crime, and not the unſatiable covetouſneſs of the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> by this cruel trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery to gain the ſole trade of the <hi>Molluccos, Banda</hi> and <hi>Amboyna,</hi>
                     <pb n="64" facs="tcp:169753:48"/>which is already become the event of this bloudy proceſs.</p>
                  <p>To adde hereunto by way of aggravation, will be needleſs; the fact is ſo full of odious and bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous inhumanity, executed by <hi>Hollanders</hi> upon the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in a place where both lived under Terms of partnerſhip and great amity, confirmed by a moſt ſolemn Treaty.</p>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:169753:48" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>A TRUE DECLARATION Of the News that came out of the <hi>Eaſt-Indies,</hi> with the <hi>Pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace</hi> called the HARE, arrived in <hi>Texel</hi> in <hi>June,</hi> 1624. CONCERNING <hi>A</hi> Conſpiracie <hi>diſcovered in the</hi> Iſland <hi>of</hi> Amboyna, <hi>and the puniſhment following thereupon, according to the courſe of Juſtice, in</hi> March 1624. <hi>compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended in a Letter</hi> Miſſive; AND SENT From a Friend in the <hi>Low-Countries,</hi> to a Friend of note in <hi>England,</hi> for information of him in the Truth of thoſe paſſages.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Printed,</hi> Anno 1651.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:169753:49"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:169753:49"/>
                  <head>Right Worſhipfull, and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy SIR,</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THe great out-cries which have been made in</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>upon the laſt News which came out of the</hi> Eaſt-Indies, <hi>about a certain execution which was done in the</hi> Iſland <hi>of</hi> Amboyna, <hi>in</hi> March 1623: <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we ſee the great deſire that your Worſhip hath, to keep good correſpondence betwixt theſe two Nations, it hath cauſed me (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond my own curioſity) to ſearch, and inquire after the right and true beginnings, proceedings, and iſſues of theſe affairs, upon which this execution followed. Wherein, I perſwade my ſelf, I have attained good ſucceſs, by ſuch means as I have uſed, and by my good ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance, ſo that (at the laſt) I am come to the clear light of the matter: partly by the Letters that have been ſent home to the</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany <hi>here, and declared to the</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:169753:50"/>States General, <hi>as alſo by a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular examination of the proceſs made againſt them in</hi> Amboyna, <hi>before their execution, and ſent over hither in writing, which at this preſent hath cauſed me to write this unto your</hi> Worſhip, <hi>that ſo, the truth may be made known concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this buſineſs in all places, where your Worthineſs, and reſpect, can, or may bring it to paſs; that ſo your</hi> Worſhip, <hi>and all true well-willers (of our Countrey,) may be no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe thought of than we deſerve.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="account">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:169753:50"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>A True</hi> Declaration <hi>of the News that came out of the</hi> Eaſt-Indies, <hi>with the</hi> Pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace <hi>called the</hi> HARE, <hi>which arrived in</hi> Texel, <hi>in</hi> June, 1624.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He very cauſes and beginnings through which, the <hi>Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour,</hi> and <hi>Councel,</hi> eſtabliſhed in the name of the United <hi>Neatherlands</hi> in <hi>Amboyna,</hi> came into ſuſpicion, that ſome thing was plotted againſt that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince; did firſt flow from the great licentiouſneſs of the <hi>Tarnatanes</hi> in <hi>Moluque,</hi> and <hi>Amboyna:</hi> Who, contrarie to the contract of alli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance 1606. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="A"/> made with the High and Mighty Lords the States, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted (without our conſent and knowledge,) to make peace with the King of <hi>Tidore:</hi> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="B"/> as alſo truce with the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> (their,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:169753:51"/>and our ancient adverſaries) by which, the ſaid <hi>Tarnatanes</hi> had too much caſt off all reſpect, which they, both in regard of our confederacie, and manifold aſſiſtance did owe to this State. The <hi>Spaniard</hi> alſo was maſter e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough at Sea, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="C"/> in the <hi>Moloque,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Merchants there in the <hi>Eaſt-Indies</hi> were unwilling to furniſh us with Ships of War toward the common defence, as they were bound to do, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Treaties 1619. to the number of ten. Through which, the voyages to <hi>Mannila,</hi> coming to ceaſe, the Enemy traded there, without any interruption, and procured power to ſend <hi>Gallies, Ships,</hi> and <hi>Pinnaces</hi> to the <hi>Moloque,</hi> with great ſuccours of people, and proviſion; and that becauſe, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſame (through the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Merchants) there were no Ships of War kept, as there ſhould have been.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="D"/> The Subjects of the King of <hi>Tarnata,</hi> begun to commit great inſolencies (otherwiſe than they were wont) againſt our Nation, having outragiouſly aſſaulted di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:169753:51"/>of us, divers wayes, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſlain ſome, and we notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding could not obtain any puniſhment upon them. And as one outrage (unpuniſhed) pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vokes many more, through hope of the like impunity, or other conſiderations; ſo were the ſaid <hi>Tarnatanes</hi> of <hi>Amboyna,</hi> dwelling at <hi>Loho, Cambello,</hi> and thoſe near adjoyning places proceeded fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and have armed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves at Sea, and invaded di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Iſlands, and places, ſtanding under the <hi>Neatherlands</hi> Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour in <hi>Amboyna,</hi> ſpoiling them, and killing our Subjects, and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king others, and carrying them away for Slaves. And notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the inſtant requeſt of the <hi>Neatherlands</hi> Gouernour, no ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, or Juſtice, hath fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed; but the ſaid <hi>Tarnatanes</hi> are yet gone further, and openly threatened to murder the <hi>Dutch</hi> Merchants, and to ſpoil and to burn the <hi>Logie,</hi> or <hi>Factorie,</hi> which our people have many years there enjoyed: ſo that our Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants have taken out the <hi>Dutch</hi> goods, to avoid dammage:
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:169753:52"/>And the <hi>Tarnatanes</hi> at <hi>Loho</hi> did actually ſet on fire, and ruined the ſaid <hi>Neatherlands</hi> Factorie. In the <hi>Manichels</hi> (an Iſland being under the Province of <hi>Amboyna</hi>) they have in like manner ſhortly after, burned the <hi>Neatherlands</hi> Logie, with the loſs of all the goods therein. The <hi>Neatherlands</hi> Governour, that by his preſence and Authority, he might cauſe ſuch Rebellions to ceaſe, and to give order for time to come, and alſo to ſeek ſatisfaction, and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment upon the aforeſaid inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies; went toward <hi>Loho,</hi> with a ſmall power of Sloops, and coming thereabout, was met (otherwiſe than was wont) by a Navie of Sloops of the <hi>Tarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans</hi> of <hi>Loho,</hi> ſtronger than his were. Theſe (by their confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence) gave him well to know, how little reverence they gave the <hi>Dutch</hi> Governour they braved him, without hope of reſtitution of any thing to come; ſo that, (nothing done) he was fain to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to his Caſtle of <hi>Amboyna.</hi> By reaſon of theſe things, the ſaid <hi>Tarnatanes</hi> became ſo ſtout and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:169753:52"/>daring, that they gave out open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that they would come, and ſpoil our Subjects by a general Army, with above an hundred <hi>Friggots:</hi> with theſe, they ſaid they would come againſt <hi>Amboy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> to make a univerſal ſpoil of our people; through which, there came a great fear upon the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians,</hi> ſtanding under the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection of the High and Mighty Lords the States, as alſo over the <hi>Neatherlanders.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="E"/> In the Iſlands lying far Eaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of <hi>Banda,</hi> it was alſo ſaid, and the News went currantly there, That the <hi>Hollanders</hi> were ſure enough quit of the Caſtle of <hi>Amboyna;</hi> And at that time there were divers ſecret correſponden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies between the <hi>Indians,</hi> &amp; others, which gave us great ſuſpition. By this means the <hi>Neatherlands</hi> Governour, and Councel of <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boyna,</hi> were moved to have ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial regard, and look narrowly unto all things, ſeeing that it might be thence clearly gathered, that ſomething might be plotted againſt the State in <hi>Amboyna,</hi> and that the <hi>Indians</hi> (of themſelves)
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:169753:53"/>durſt not offer to undertake any ſuch great deſign, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="F"/> without ſome great help of ſome of <hi>Europe,</hi> ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of <hi>Spaniarnds, Portugals,</hi> or ſome other; and alſo, they un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, that they of <hi>Loho, Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bello,</hi> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="G"/> &amp;c. had great ſecret cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondence with the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Merchants. When things were in ſuch a ſtate in <hi>Amboyna,</hi> there came forth and was wonderfully diſcovered, in February 1623. a horrible conſpiracie againſt the Caſtle, and Perſon of the <hi>Dutch</hi> Governour, and the whole ſtate of <hi>Amboyna:</hi> and firſt, by the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of a certain <hi>Iaponian</hi> (a complice of the feat) who at an unſeaſonable time was often ſeen upon the wall of the Caſtle, where he alſo over-curiouſly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of the moſt unskilfull and fillieſt Souldiers, touching the ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and change of the Watch, and what number of people might be in the Caſtle, and many other things. Whereupon, in the very Act, the ſaid <hi>Iaponian</hi> was appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended, and being examined of many circumſtances, he confeſſed that the <hi>Iaponian</hi> Souldiers un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:169753:53"/>our ſervice, had decreed to make themſelves Maſters of the Caſtle, and that they ſhould have ſet upon this by the help of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> who had ſolicited them unto it; and that he, with all the other <hi>Japonians</hi> in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> houſe, often-times within three Moneths before-going, had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred with the <hi>Engliſh</hi> (whom he there named, by their names) touching the manner, whereby they ſhould bring this treacherie to paſs, Hereupon it came to paſs, that all the <hi>Japonian</hi> Souldiers, which were in our ſervice, were diſarmed, and impriſoned, and by examination of them all, it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared plainly, by an orderly and joynt-confeſſion, that all the ſaid <hi>Japonians,</hi> upon the intreaty of <hi>Gabriel Towerſon,</hi> and other <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> Merchants &amp; Officers agreed to aſſiſt the ſaid <hi>Engliſh,</hi> to betray the Caſtle, and to give it over into the <hi>Engliſh</hi> power: &amp; that <hi>Gabriel Towerſon,</hi> and <hi>Abel Price</hi> (an <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> Chirurgion) and other <hi>Engliſh</hi> dealt often with them (whom he named by their names) of the way and means, how they ſhould work
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:169753:54"/>it; the ſaid <hi>Abel Price</hi> being before impriſoned, for a foul, and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crable fact, and yet remaining in durance.</p>
                  <p>And although it appeared ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently to the Governour, and Councel of <hi>Amboyna,</hi> out of the confeſſion of the <hi>Japonians,</hi> what the ſaid <hi>Gabriel Towerſon</hi> with his Merchants and other Complices, had before reſolved to do, and that the Councel had ſufficient information to impriſon them all; yet the General Councel would not precipitate, but commanded the ſaid <hi>Abel Price,</hi> (who was in priſon) to come before the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel, and (after the places perſons, &amp; time, nominated to him, where and when he had dealt with the <hi>Japonians,</hi> and other Engliſh, about the ſaid treachery) it was alſo from him well underſtood, how he (in the name, and by the command of <hi>Gabriel Towerſon</hi>) and another <hi>Japonian,</hi> (who was then alſo in priſon) had perſwaded all the <hi>Iaponians,</hi> to conſent to this villany, and that conſequently the ſaid <hi>Towerſon,</hi> as the firſt Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour, and all the other Engliſh
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:169753:54"/>Merchants, (being in the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign <hi>Cantore</hi> of the Province of <hi>Amboyna</hi>) had alſo knowledge of the ſaid treacherie.</p>
                  <p>Upon this full and unifom exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, and confeſſion of 12 perſons, as well of the 11 <hi>Japo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians,</hi> as one Engliſh, is the ſaid <hi>Gabriel Towerſon</hi> called to the Councel, and there appearing, the ſaid <hi>Towerſon</hi> called together all his people unto the Caſtle, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the requeſt of the General Councel, who were there taken, &amp; impriſoned, except the ſaid <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briel Towerſon</hi> himſelf, to whom (upon his requeſt) and in regard of his qualitie, being chief Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant in <hi>Amboyna,</hi> in the name of the Engliſh Companie; his own houſe was allotted him for his ſafe keeping, and forth-coming, And the ſaid Priſoners were all lawfully and orderly examined, and it appeared by them jointly, according to their own confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion (every one having under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>written it with his own hand) as followeth:</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="H"/> 
                     <hi>Gabriel Towerſon,</hi> about New-years day 1623. having with him
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:169753:55"/>almoſt all the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Merchants of the forreign <hi>Cantore</hi> in <hi>Amboy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> he aſſembled them in his Chamber, and propounded to them, that he had ſomething of great moment to impart unto them, (which he alone could not effect) under the fidelity of an Oath to be taken before, for the keeping ſecret thereof, and being truſty therein; ſaying, It is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie ſo to be: for if the thing ſhould come abroad, which I ſhall make known unto you, it will coſt all our lives. Whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the holy Goſpel was produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, upon which, every one, who was preſent did ſwear ſecrecie &amp; fidelitie, as was required. Then <hi>Towerſon</hi> (after a Preface) opened to the conſpiratours, how he had a way and means to make himſelf Maſter of the Caſtle of <hi>Amboyna.</hi> And whereas ſome preſent made it difficult to do, being too weak for it: the ſaid <hi>Towerſon</hi> anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> That he had already won to his purpoſe the <hi>Iaponian</hi> Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers who were in the Caſtle, and that they ſhould execute his purpoſe when the <hi>Dutch,</hi> who
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:169753:55"/>were in the Caſtle, were in their greateſt weakneſs: and worſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided, or (unawares) when the Governour ſhould be abſent, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout ſome exploit; and that they ſhould wait till ſome <hi>Engliſh</hi> Ships, or Ship, were in <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boyna,</hi> whoſe People he might employ in this attempt; as alſo, when as all other the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Merchants, and ſlaves of the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign <hi>Cantore</hi> in <hi>Amboyna,</hi> ſhould be ſent for to the Caſtle. And ſaid further, That he knew how to get men enough, &amp; they ſhould leave this to his care, and them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to their beſt; and that they of <hi>Lobo</hi> ſhould alſo come to help him with certain <hi>Corrercorens,</hi> &amp;c. Upon which induceme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, all that were preſent ſwore to aſſiſt <hi>Tower<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> herein. And concerning the manner of Execution, the ſaid <hi>Towerſon</hi> had preſcribed to the <hi>Japonians,</hi> which were in the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, that they ſhould ſend to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry point of the Bulwarks two men, and the reſt, in the Court at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the Governour, and to mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him, &amp; that at the ſign which ſhould be given to the <hi>Engliſh,</hi>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:169753:56"/>they ſhould make themſelves Maſters of every point of the bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wark, and kill all who ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt, and impriſon the reſt; and further ſhould take, and divide between themſelves, and the <hi>Japo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians,</hi> the goods of the Dutch Eaſt Indian Company, except a thouſand Royals of eights; which every <hi>Japonian</hi> ſhould have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and that they ſhould kill the Citizens, who would not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent with them, and do them all the miſchief they could. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="K"/> And touching the time, he had not yet certainly ſet it, but that there ſhould ſuddenly be another aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly of the conſpiratours, when <hi>Gabriel Towerſon</hi> would give or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der for all things, and give a ſign to the <hi>Japonians,</hi> whereupon, when they ſhewed it, they ſhould begin the work within.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="L"/> The ſaid <hi>Gabriel Towerſon</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing asked in particular; what moved him to ſuch a wicked fact; he anſwered, the deſire of Honour and profit. Being fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>there demanded, who ſhould in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy that Honour and Profit, and for whom he would have taken
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:169753:56"/>the Caſtle: he anſwered, That if he did obtain his deſire, he ſhould preſently have advertiſed thoſe of his Nation being in <hi>Batavia,</hi> and called for their help, who if they had ſent him ſuccour, he would have kept the Caſtle for his own Company, <hi>viz.</hi> (for the <hi>Engliſh Eaſt-Indian</hi> Company) and if not, he would have held it for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and have endeavoured a peace with the <hi>Indians,</hi> that ſo by the one means or the other, he might attain his purpoſe. After the examination of <hi>Towerſon</hi> was ended, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="M"/> the <hi>Dutch</hi> Governour in <hi>Amboyna</hi> upbraided <hi>Towerſon</hi> of his cruel intent, and asked, if this ſhould have been the recompence of the manifold honours, and kindneſſes he had done unto him. Whereto <hi>Towerſon</hi> anſwered with a deep ſigh, Oh, if it were to be begun, it ſhould not be done. This voluntarie confeſſion, and penitent acknowledgement, with much ſorrow, was made the 9. of March, being the day when the execution ſhould have been done; but the examination of <hi>Towerſon</hi> was ended the 18. of February,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:169753:57"/>ſo many dayes before. This is the ſubſtance of the confeſſions of 10 <hi>Japonians,</hi> of 14 <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and of a <hi>Neatherlandiſh Merinho,</hi> or Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of the Slaves; who all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed theſe their confeſſions with their own hands.</p>
                  <p>What crime this intended pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition was, is hence very manifeſt, and undoubted: what puniſhment is due to treacherie, according to the Law and Cuſtoms of all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, is alſo well known: no true Chriſtian man will patronage any ſuch horrible attempt, but will ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judge it worthy of death, as it was determined upon the compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of this conſpiracie, according to order of Juſtice, as there in <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boyna</hi> it is exerciſed (according to deſert) by the Governour and Councel, in the name of the High and Mighty Lords, the <hi>States.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Here you have (Sir) the very ſubſtance of the Truth, both of the Fact and puniſhment; other than which, many things are ſpread abroad in <hi>England,</hi> but up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on what pretence, or intendment, I know not; let the matter it ſelf ſpeak for it ſelf.</p>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:169753:57"/>
                  <p>The firſt point, <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>1</label> which is obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted againſt this Juſtice done in <hi>Amboyna,</hi> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="N"/> is concerning the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings; which are ſaid to be holden without formality, and with extremity, againſt theſe conſpiratours: Your <hi>Worſhip</hi> (and each reaſonable man) know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that every land hath their Laws and Ordinances, and their particular manner of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, as well in Civil as in Criminal cauſes. <hi>England</hi> hath hers, <hi>France, Spain, Dutchland, Neatherland,</hi> and all other King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms and Governments have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo theirs, which are juſt and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to every one in their Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion; ſo that, when any man will judge of the equitie or injuſtice of a proceeding uſed in any Land, he muſt examine the ſame ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Laws &amp; cuſtoms of that Kingdom or Dominion, where the Juſtice &amp; Proceedings were holden. Theſe Proceedings were holden by the <hi>Neatherland<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh</hi> Governour, in the name of the Illuſtrious Lords, the <hi>States,</hi> having ſupream Power, many years ſince in the <hi>Iſles</hi> of <hi>Amboyna,</hi>
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:169753:58"/>which were conquered (in the name of the ſaid Lords, the <hi>States</hi>) from the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> or <hi>Portugals,</hi> who held that Caſtle in the name of the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> our heredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie enemy; therefore they are now poſſeſſed in the name of the Lords, the <hi>States,</hi> and are under their Dominion, by a juſt and Lawfull Title of War, according to the Law of Nations. There (among other things) Juſtice is adminiſtred according to the Law of the <hi>Neatherlands,</hi> in that manner as was uſed in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings againſt theſe conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours. I know that the Laws of <hi>England</hi> are divers from ours in <hi>Criminal</hi> caſes, yea, and from all the Nations in <hi>Europe:</hi> howbeit therefore, no man hath any ground of reaſon to ſay, that the proceedings of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> judges (holden in <hi>England</hi>) againſt De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquents, are not legitimate, though the ſaid <hi>Engliſh</hi> proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings do varie in the manner from the proceedings of <hi>France, Spain,</hi> &amp;c. where other cuſtoms are: for that is lawfull, which agreeth with the Laws of that Land
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:169753:58"/>where the fact is committed. Now then the <hi>Japonian</hi> Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, being in the ſervice of the <hi>Neatherlands</hi> Company in <hi>Amboy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> are discovered to have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired againſt the Caſtle, and the Governour there, under whoſe Oath and pay they were; they were apprehended, and examined, and convicted of the ſaid conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racie. This proceeding is Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and toucheth no man, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the ſaid <hi>Japonians</hi> knew no other Maſter than the <hi>Neather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landers,</hi> under whoſe Oath, ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and pay they ſtand. All theſe <hi>Japonian</hi> conſpiratours with the ſaid <hi>Merincho,</hi> a Captain of the <hi>Neatherlands</hi> Slaves, confeſſed with one mouth, that they were moved and induced to this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracie, by the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants reſident in <hi>Amboyna,</hi> whoſe names they named. Now, not onely the right of <hi>Neatherland,</hi> but of <hi>England,</hi> and of the whole World requireth, that the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thours, abettours and complices of Murder and Treaſon, ſhould be puniſhed with death; whereto, according to the common Laws,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:169753:59"/>as alſo the particular Laws of every Kingdom or Dominion, the ſuſpected perſons firſt, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all, ſhould be impriſoned, not onely for preventing the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of their evil purpoſe, but that they might alſo receive their deſerved puniſhment: which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions, could not (in that place) be done by any other man, than by the command of the <hi>Neatherlands</hi> Governour, to whom it belongeth to take care, to ſee every act concerning Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream power to be there obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="O"/> and eſpecially (all other reaſons ceaſing) the higheſt <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> Officers there, could not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend theſe <hi>Engliſh</hi> Conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours, becauſe all the chief of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Merchants in <hi>Amboyna</hi> were themſelves of the conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, and complices of the fact, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which the apprehenſion was made. Therefore the apprehenſion of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> complices muſt be done by the <hi>Dutch</hi> Governour, who therefore hath therein pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded according to the cuſtom of all Nations of the world. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="P"/> And that theſe apprehenſions may be
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:169753:59"/>holden more Lawfull; it appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth out of the written proceſs, that the ſaid <hi>Engliſh</hi> complices were not impriſoned upon the firſt ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpitions &amp; groſs evidences, which were had againſt them, but then at laſt, when all the <hi>Japonian</hi> Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers were taken, examined, and convicted, and had diſcovered by the uniform confeſſion of all the eleven, the names and ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>names of ſuch <hi>Engliſh</hi> as had per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded and hired them to this fact; of which <hi>Engliſh,</hi> viz. (one <hi>Abel Price,</hi> Barber) was before apprehended (as an <hi>Incendiary</hi>) for burning and violence done upon other houſes, who alſo was firſt examined &amp; firſt confeſſed (as the other 11 <hi>Japonians</hi>) that he (by name, <hi>Gabriel Towerſon</hi>) &amp; other <hi>Engliſh</hi> Merchants, whom he na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by their names, had ſuborned the ſaid <hi>Japonian</hi> Souldiers, and that all the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Merchants in the Forreign <hi>Cantores</hi> in <hi>Amboy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> had knowledge of this conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racie, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So that it may be ſeen, out of that which went before, that the <hi>Dutch</hi> Governour dealt no otherwiſe in the apprehenſion,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:169753:60"/>and examination of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> than according to his place, and power, and that with great diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion, according to the Laws of theſe United Provinces.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Q"/> The ſecond point which is abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſively diſperſed in <hi>England,</hi> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Oubject </seg>2</label> againſt this execution, is, that it is ſaid, that it did not appertain to the <hi>Neatherlanders</hi> in <hi>Amboyna</hi> to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſon the ſaid <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and to proceed againſt them, or to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh them; but that it did belong to the Councel of Defence reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent at <hi>Jaccatra,</hi> conſiſting half of <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and half of <hi>Neather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landers,</hi> according to the Treaty of the year 1619. made between his <hi>Majeſtie</hi> and the Lords the States, between the two <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Companies. That I might the better inform my ſelf thereof, I took in hand, and peruſed the general Treaty of 1619. with the explication following there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon; but I profeſs, that (as I think) every underſtanding man, (not loving diſcord) muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, that neither in the ſaid Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, nor in the enlargement, any one Article or word could be
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:169753:60"/>perceived, whereby (according to that which is untruely ſaid in <hi>England</hi>) either this, or any ſuch thing is ordained, or decided, by the ſaid Treaty, as it ought to have clearly been in ſo great and important a point, as this part of Juriſdiction is. I appeal to all wiſe men, who I deſire may judge of this, whether this ſpeech of ſome in <hi>England</hi> (to wit, that the ſaid Councel of defence ſhould (alone) have judged theſe conſpiratours) be agreable to the ſaid Treaty, or contrarie to the ſame. I find many Arguments for my Negative opinions, to wit, that before the Treaty of 1619. the <hi>Duch</hi> in <hi>Amboyna</hi> adminiſtred Juriſdiction, and Judicature, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all and every one who dwelt in or under the Juriſdiction of the Caſtle, as well inhabitants as ſtrangers, without difference; and that in this ſaid Treaty, the <hi>Dutch,</hi> with the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, made onely a league in the matter of commerce and Nego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation of <hi>Nutmegs, Mace, Cloves;</hi> and <hi>Pepper,</hi> in ſome quarters, without having any further Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:169753:61"/>or communication in the land; ſo that without the bounds of this common Negotiation, every one remained free, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hindered in the land by the right and poſſeſſion which either Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany enjoyed, and exerciſed ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, according as the ſame ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth out of the 23 Article of the Treatie: where it is expreſly ſaid, <hi>That caſtles and Furts ſhall remain</hi> in their hands who at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent do poſſeſs them: And out of the 13.14.15. Articles of the Treatie, all may ſee, that this common Councel of Defence hath no more power, ſave onely over the fellowſhip of the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, that is, over the Navie of defence in the Sea, to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the common Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize, and liberty of commerce; and laſtly, to tax the charges for the proviſion of ammunition in the Forts: neither can any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing be ſincerely collected out of the ſaid Treaty, ſo far as I can conceive. Therefore this ſecond point is found to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>true and abuſive, being not founded upon the ſaid Treatie,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:169753:61"/>which Treatie (not withſtanding) ought to be the onely rule, both of the one and the other Company.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="R"/> Finally, it is given out in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> that in the examination of the Conſpiratours there was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs in the <hi>Neatherlands</hi> Judges, in the point of Torture: I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, that no argument or pretext againſt the Juſtice of this execution, hath more moved me in the beginning, than this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of exceſs aforeſaid, becauſe this ſtirreth Chriſtian compaſſion; although I alſo judge, that wiſe men will not ſuffer themſelves to be too much tranſported thereby, before the true reaſons do fully appear, which ſhould move us thereunto. For, I well remember yet, that in the time of former mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtakings in the <hi>Indies</hi> many things were pretended on both parts, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which, there were great outcries one either ſide, which yet, by due examination, were found to be (though fair, yet) falſe pretexts of ſome ill-willers, and men deſirous to wrangle: which pretences being throughly ſifted by the High and much admired wiſdom of his <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty,</hi>
                     <pb n="24" facs="tcp:169753:62"/>&amp; the Lords, the <hi>States,</hi> were well diſcovered to be no ſuch matters as they were made: as it is alſo undoubtedly to be believed, that his <hi>Majeſty,</hi> and the <hi>States,</hi> will yet further do in this affair: and ſo the cauſe of the <hi>Dutch</hi> Company may be (in the carriage hereof) rightly juſtified. Of which I underſtand that the Lords the <hi>States</hi> have ſpecial re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard, and that they have been throughly informed, what is the very truth of the things there paſt, and of the Execution in <hi>Amboyna</hi> upon the <hi>Engliſh</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiratours. Unto which end the Lords the <hi>States</hi> reſolved to ſee and peruſe all the Papers and Letters, touching the ſaid pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings: And now thereupon men ſpeak far otherwiſe than heretofore; for pretences, and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils (being once detected) cannot ſtand with truth. And it doth plainly appear, that there is little truth in the matter of Torture, reported to be moſt cruelly infli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted upon theſe <hi>Engliſh</hi> conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratours, as in <hi>England</hi> it is ſaid. And I have ever ſuſpected this
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:169753:62"/>for a ſlander: for I know the <hi>Dutch</hi> Nation doth naturally ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor this kind of cruelty, and are as much moved to commiſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as any other people. But whether theſe evil minded men, who have ſcattered this great ſlander in <hi>England,</hi> and have ſo fowly defaced a juſt cauſe, have done it by occaſion of our uſe of Tortures in theſe Lands, in ſome weighty cauſes, according to the cuſtom of the moſt Dominions of <hi>Europe;</hi> I cannot Judge. But is that to be cenſured &amp; Judged to be unjuſt of the whole world, which is repugnant to the Laws of <hi>England,</hi> (or any one Nation) where Torture is rarely uſed? Nothing ſo; but the Juſtice or injuſtice of a cauſe muſt be (as aforeſaid) determined, according to the Laws where it is done, and not of other Lands. If this were not ſo, why then ſhould not the whole World much more Judge that as a hard, &amp; a thing unheard (and therefore condemnable) which in ſome cauſes is uſed in <hi>England,</hi> according to the Laws there, when they proceed againſt
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:169753:63"/>ſome guiltie perſons; who being once &amp; again asked of the Judge, and utterly refuſing to be legally tried, is adjudged as dumb, that is, by contumacie; whoſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation then accordingly fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth, that he is laid upon a ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, or plank, and another plank upon him, and ſo much weight of ſtone or lead laid upon him, that his body is miſerably bruiſed, and ſo preſſed violently to death. The which, according to the conſeſſion of all Nations, (eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, becauſe this kind of juſtice is not uſed in other Lands) and by the <hi>Engliſh</hi> writers, is judged to be one of the moſt ſharp and ſevere kinds of death, that can be invented; yet cannot ſuch an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution be called cruel and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull, when it is done in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> becauſe it is done accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Laws of that Land, though ſtrangers ſhall judge o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe of it. And in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation cannot complain of the Torture which evil-willers ſay, was uſed upon theſe <hi>Engliſh</hi> Conſpiratours in <hi>Amboyna,</hi> becauſe it is done ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:169753:63"/>to the Laws of this Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and is not unuſual in caſes of Treaſon, neither with-us, nor (almoſt) any Nation in <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope.</hi> And for <hi>England</hi> it ſelf, it is well known (and his moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent <hi>Majeſty</hi> doth acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge by his own Princely pen) that the <hi>Rack,</hi> and the <hi>Manicles,</hi> are the onely Tortures, that are exerciſed upon Traitors, to force them to confeſs, (<hi>without conceal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi>) what they know to be dangerous to the <hi>State.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And to ſay the Truth, without taking parts, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratours being affronted with the uniform &amp; written confeſſions of the 11 <hi>Japonians</hi> (their complices) which could convince them ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently according to the laws, &amp; find them guilty of the ſame con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracie, &amp; conſequently of death: if now, not withſtanding this they had perſiſted in the ſtout denial of the fact, were not this, (to (ſpeak according to the manner in <hi>England</hi>) enough to judge them dumb by contumacie, and ſo to eſteem them worthy of this ſore puniſhment of Preſſing to
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:169753:64"/>death, as is afore-ſaid? but this tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of ours (if any in <hi>Amboyna</hi> were ſo tortured) is to be judged far leſs, than that preſſing, where the Malefactor doth ſuffer ſuch extream miſerie, as cannot be imagined, and which is not to be lenified or eaſed at all, but ended by death. But to the ſufficient fatisfaction of my ſelf, and your Worſhip, and all men, and not to ſpeak according to the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, and conſcience of others; I have uſed all diligence to get into my hands the written <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs,</hi> concerning the Conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours in <hi>Amboyna,</hi> which I ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained authentically, and read carefully, and I find, that all, that is by me aboveſaid, is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed, to wit, That the <hi>Japonian</hi> Complices were examined, and made their confeſſions as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, for three dayes, <hi>viz.</hi> the 23, 24, 25. of <hi>February,</hi> 1623. and that all this being done, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummated before, then at laſt, is <hi>Gabriel Towerſon,</hi> firſt with the reſt of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Complices im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned, the ſaid 25. of <hi>Febru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary,</hi> when their examination and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:169753:64"/>confeſſion began, &amp; continued di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers dayes, without over-haſting till the third of <hi>March.</hi> And the ſaid examinations and confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons being ſo finiſhed, the <hi>Neather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands</hi> Governour and Councel, deliberated whether the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment might be deferred to any long time, or referred to any other place; but it was ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded by joynt conſent of all, that the ſaid puniſhment (there deſerved) muſt be executed in the ſame place for example, and that it could not (in any wiſe) be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layed without extream danger, for reaſons there related; and among others', becauſe the <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natanes,</hi> and <hi>Indians</hi> about <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boyna,</hi> had otherwiſe than they were wont, rebelled; neither could it be fully known, what great co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federacie theſe Conſpiratours had made with them, and others. And touching any extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and cruel Torture, I have ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curatly over-looked every ones confeſſion, but I find not one word in any one, which maketh any mention of ſuch Torture, as is unjuſtly ſpoken of in <hi>England;</hi>
                     <pb n="30" facs="tcp:169753:65"/>nay, ſcarce find any mention of that ordinarie Torture, which is in uſe, ſave onely theſe words, in one act of the 25 February 1623. viz. <hi>The Councel being gathered to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, have thought meet, that all the</hi> Engliſh <hi>ſhould be preſently ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined one after another (as accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly it was inſtantly done) and ſome of them,</hi> before any torture, others, after a little (or rather a touch) of it, <hi>confeſſed as followeth.</hi> Unto which, followeth preſently, the particular confeſſion of each one, ſubſcribed with his own hand, as aforeſaid. So that hence it is manifeſt, that no extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie Torture was uſed, in ſuch manner as is given out there, by thoſe that wiſh us evil; nay, that thoſe few that felt any, were one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly touched (not puniſhed) with ordinarie Torture.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="S"/> And thus your Worſhip hath the upright, and impartial truth of this buſineſs, touching the whole paſſage as it proceeded, and the puniſhment as it was inflicted; from which, ſome <hi>Engliſh</hi> were exempted by favour, that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> goods ſhould not be loſt,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:169753:65"/>cording as order hath been given to that end: And I find that the ſentence was given the ninth of <hi>March</hi> 1623. by a competent aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly of 14 Judges; who, (as it appeareth in the ſentence) in the doing thereof did (before) earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly call upon the Name of the Lord, that he would pleaſe to be Preſident and Predominant in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one of their hearts in this their <hi>ſorrowfull aſsembly;</hi> and that he would inſpire them onely with that which might be judged to be expedient and juſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So that out of all that is above ſaid, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe can appear, but that this buſineſs was managed lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and orderly, by men of hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty and conſcience, againſt ſuch as had undertaken againſt the <hi>State,</hi> againſt the wealth and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of this <hi>East-India</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, the lives of their Officers there placed, againſt the eſtate and welfare of many, who had little deſerved, and as little ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected ſuch wickedneſs from their friendly confederates in the ſame ſocietie of Merchants, there reſident with them.</p>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:169753:66"/>
                  <p>And now (conſidering the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſes) I hope it ſhall be far from every Chriſtian in any wiſe to protect or excuſe this wicked Fact, but rather to mourn and grieve (as we do) for this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracie, and for the evil, the Conſpiratours have ſo deſerved<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly drawn upon their own heads; and to honour them, who in Juſtice have puniſhed villany, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the due merit thereof; for we all know, that without JUSTICE, without reward of that which is <hi>Good,</hi> and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of that which is <hi>Evil,</hi> no ſocietie of mankind can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt.</p>
                  <p>And of this information, (which I ſend in love, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to your <hi>Worſhip,</hi> as unto <hi>a lover of Truth,</hi> and <hi>a hater of Treacherie</hi>) you may make ſuch uſe, as to you ſhall ſeem good, in any place where you come, both for <hi>refutation</hi> of any thing alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy reported contrarie thereunto, and for <hi>prevention</hi> of any further falſe rumours, or clamours; and finally, for <hi>propagation</hi> of that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted truth, which <hi>here</hi> (to
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:169753:66"/>my beſt) I have endeavoured to diſcover. And if you ſhall meet with any thing of worth; which can be truly avowed, to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictorie unto any thing I have written, I deſire to underſtand it from you, and you to ſuſpend your wiſe and impartial judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, till I have cleared it unto you. TRUTH remaineth ever the ſame. So I commend you to the <hi>God of Truth,</hi> deſiring him to give us minds, <hi>Not to judge according to outward appearance, but to judge with a righteous judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>From my Lodging, <date>
                           <hi>July</hi> 23. 1624.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="account">
                  <pb facs="tcp:169753:67"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:169753:67"/>
                  <head>AN ANSWER To the <hi>Dutch</hi> Relation, touching the Pretended <hi>Conſpiracie</hi> of the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> at AMBOYNA in the <hi>Indies.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He <hi>Compiler</hi> of this Relation, percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving that he had an hard task to make it probable, that eighteen <hi>Engliſhmen</hi> Merchants and their ſervants, all un-armed, ſhould, with the help and aſſiſtance of ten <hi>Japons,</hi> like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe un-armed, undertake the ſurprize of a Caſtle, ſo provided every way, as that of <hi>Amboyna,</hi> is before in the Relation of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> truly deſcribed to be: as alſo the ſame Author, well weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that albeit all that he was to write of this pretended <hi>Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racie,</hi>
                     <pb n="36" facs="tcp:169753:68"/>ſhould be taken for true, yet the fact would ſeem very poor to bear ſo rigorous a puniſhment in perſons of that quality, and of that Relation to thoſe that inflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it; provides more skilfully than fairly, for both theſe points in the preamble of this Relation: To this end, he rakes and heaps together all the jealouſies and dangers that the <hi>Dutch</hi> had in the <hi>Indies:</hi> yea, and more than they truly had, at or about the time of the pretended conſpiracie, and applies them all to the ſuſpicion of this buſineſs: as if all their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies were likely to conſpire with the <hi>Engliſh;</hi> and therefore the fact, under colour whereof they were condemned and executed, were poſſible and probable; and as if the ſtate of the time had been then ſo dangerous, that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſhadow of conſpiracie was to be exquiſitely enquired of, &amp; the leaſt offence to be ſeverely puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Wherefore although this be no direct charge of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> but uſed by the Author to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply the want of probabilities in the proceſs it ſelf, it will not be
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:169753:68"/>amiſs to examin the ſeveral cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, and how far they may yield any ſuſpicion againſt the ſaid <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="A"/> Now this Authour taketh the main grounds of this ſuſpicion of ſome great plot againſt the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince of <hi>Amboyna,</hi> from the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wonted boldneſs and inſolencies of the <hi>Ternatans;</hi> firſt in the <hi>Mol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luccos,</hi> and then in <hi>Amboyna.</hi> For thoſe in the <hi>Molluccos,</hi> he ſaith, they had lately before the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended conſpiracie of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> gone about, contrarie to the Treatie, Anno 1606. between them and the <hi>Dutch,</hi> to make peace with the King of <hi>Tedore,</hi> and truce with the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> without the conſent or know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of them, the <hi>Dutch:</hi> which how honeſtly and conſcionably it is alleadged to this purpoſe, may appear by the Journals of thoſe parts, which evidently ſhew, that this Treaty between thoſe of <hi>Ternata</hi> and <hi>Tedore,</hi> was in <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember</hi> 1621. that is to ſay, fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen Moneths before this forged conſpiragie; and that with the knowledge of <hi>Houtman,</hi> the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:169753:69"/>of the <hi>Dutch,</hi> who, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the 19 of <hi>November</hi> the year aforeſaid, acquainted M. <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chols,</hi> the Agent of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> in thoſe parts, with the prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of this Treatie, which was actually holden at <hi>Ternata</hi> the 24 of the ſame moneth. But the matter was ſo well handled by the <hi>Dutch,</hi> to keep thoſe neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour Iſlands in perpetual War, that the Treatie was diſſolved <hi>re infecta:</hi> And the ſeventh of <hi>December</hi> following, an Edict was publiſhed by the King of <hi>Ternata,</hi> commanding all the <hi>Tedorians</hi> forth with to depart the Iſland of <hi>Ternata,</hi> upon pain to be made Slaves. After this, the correſpondence between the <hi>Dutch</hi> and <hi>Ternatans</hi> in the <hi>Mol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luccoes,</hi> returned into as firm ſtate as ever; the <hi>Ternatans</hi> perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing dayly exploits againſt the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and communicating the Triumph with the <hi>Dutch:</hi> As the ſeventeenth of <hi>February</hi> 1622. being a ſull year before the ſeined Treaſon of the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh,</hi> the King of <hi>Ternata,</hi> with twenty <hi>Curricurries,</hi> took a <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh</hi>
                     <pb n="5" facs="tcp:169753:69"/>Galley, ſlew forty in fight, and took 150 Priſoners, whom they ſold to the <hi>Dutch</hi> for Cloath and Rice: and coming by the <hi>Hollanders</hi> Caſtle of <hi>Maalaio,</hi> the eighteenth of the ſame Moneth, with the heads of divers <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards</hi> at his Stern, the <hi>Dutch</hi> ſaluted him from their ſaid Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle with nine ſhot of great Ord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance. The 25 of <hi>April</hi> follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the Admiral of the King of <hi>Ternata</hi> took a <hi>Prow</hi> of the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards,</hi> ſlew ſome, and ſold the reſt to the <hi>Dutch.</hi> The 28 of the ſame Moneth, both <hi>Dutch</hi> and <hi>Engliſh</hi> were feaſted by the King of <hi>Ternata.</hi> The 22 of May next enſuing, the King of <hi>Ternata</hi> went forth to <hi>Machian</hi> with ſix <hi>Curricurries,</hi> and at his departure was honoured with thirty ſhot of great Ordinance from the <hi>Dutch</hi> Caſtle. The 15 of <hi>June</hi> the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miral of the King of <hi>Ternata</hi> made a Voyage towards <hi>Minda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>now,</hi> carrying divers of the <hi>Dutch</hi> with him to aſſiſt him. The third of July the <hi>Ternatanes</hi> took other Priſoners, and ſold them to the <hi>Dutch.</hi> The 24 of <hi>Auguſt</hi> the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:169753:70"/>King of <hi>Ternata</hi> made one <hi>Vogler</hi> a Dutch Merchant his Treaſurer; at whoſe inſtalment in his new Office, the <hi>Dutch</hi> gave ſeven great ſhot from the Caſtle. And this good correſpondence, between the <hi>Ternatans</hi> and the <hi>Dutch</hi> in the <hi>Molluccos,</hi> continued even untill, and after the execution of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> at <hi>Amboyna:</hi> which was (as hath been ſhewed) in <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bruary,</hi> 1623. <hi>New ſtile.</hi> Upon the 14 of which Moneth, the <hi>Dutch</hi> gave the King of <hi>Ternata,</hi> and other <hi>Blacks,</hi> two hundred Bails of <hi>Japan</hi> Rice, with other preſents: at the delivery where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, there were ſhot off from the Caſtle ſeven pieces of Ordnance, and three Vollies of ſmall ſhot. By all which may appear, how fmceerly this Authour applieth the diffidence between the <hi>Dutch</hi> and the King of <hi>Ternata,</hi> which was now none at all, to this bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs of <hi>Amboyna.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="B"/> The next point is, that the <hi>Ternatans</hi> in the <hi>Molluccos</hi> went about alſo to make truce with the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> without conſent or knowledge of the <hi>Dutch;</hi> wherein
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:169753:70"/>this dealing of the Authour is worſe than the former. For this Treatie of truce appeareth by the Journals, to have been holden the 19 of July 1623. which was five moneths after the execution of the Engliſh at <hi>Amboyna,</hi> and ſo came too late to move ſuſpition againſt them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="C"/> And yet this pretended fear and jealouſie of the <hi>Molluccos</hi> is further amplified by the ſtrength of the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> being then (as this Authour affirmeth) Maſter of the Sea there, and that by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault of the Engliſh; who, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to the Treatie of the year 1619, had deſerted the defence, and ſent no more ſhips, neither to the <hi>Molluccos,</hi> nor to the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nilliaes:</hi> whence now the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards</hi> had means to ſend Ships, Gallies, and Pinnaces, to the <hi>Molluccos.</hi> What the ſtrength of the <hi>Spaniard</hi> in the <hi>Molluccos</hi> (by Sea) was, at the time of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended fear, may appear by the exploits before mentioned, done upon them by the <hi>Curricurries</hi> of the <hi>Ternatans,</hi> without help of the <hi>Hollanders.</hi> But for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:169753:71"/>of the Engliſh, which is here odiouſly alleadged, it will be requiſite to ſet down the true cauſes, wherefore the <hi>Engliſh</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquiſhed the action of defence, as well at the <hi>Manilliaes,</hi> as elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where; being a matter much ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravated upon all occaſions by the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> albeit themſelves have given the cauſe thereof. Wherefore ſhortly, the true mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> their deſiſting from the action of defence, were as followeth. The <hi>Engliſh</hi> had by agreement of the Councel of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, two years together main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained a Fleet of five tall &amp; war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like ſhips, to joyn with the like ſtrength of the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> for the action of the <hi>Manilliaes,</hi> and the profit of the Voyage (as the charge) to be common to both Companies. The <hi>Dutch</hi> prepared another Fleet of ſeven ſhips, all of their own, for <hi>Macao,</hi> bordering upon <hi>China,</hi> near the <hi>Manilliaes,</hi> without giving knowledge there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> at <hi>Jaccatra,</hi> until their Fleet was ready to depart thence; well knowing, that up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſuch warning it would be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:169753:71"/>for the <hi>Engliſh</hi> to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare a like force to joyn with them. To thoſe they appointed alſo eight <hi>Pinaces</hi> that were then abroad, to joyn; and afterwards ſent another Ship with proviſions unto them. This Fleet paſſing by two of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Ships, which were appointed for that quarter of the <hi>Manilliaes;</hi> the <hi>Engliſh</hi> wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comed them, and offered to joyn with them in their exploit: which the <hi>Dutch</hi> refuſed, ſaying, That this being an exploit of their own, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſhould neither parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipate of the fact, nor of the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit that might ariſe thereby. Likewiſe, by agreement of the Councel of defence of both Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, there was another Fleet of ten Ships ſet forth at the equal charge of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Dutch,</hi> for the coaſt of <hi>Malla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bar,</hi> to ſecure the Trade in that part. Of the <hi>Dutch</hi> Ships (about a moneth after they ſet ſail) two were found to be ſo weak and leak, that they were fain to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to <hi>Jaccatra.</hi> The reſt being come to their quarter, two of the beſt of the <hi>Dutch</hi> Ships were
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:169753:72"/>ſent away by the <hi>Dutch</hi> Admiral, for the Red-ſea, contrarie to their inſtructions and Commiſſion at <hi>Jaccatra</hi> from the Councel of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, and notwithſtanding the proteſtations, obteſtations and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamations of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> againſt this prevarication. So that four <hi>Caracks</hi> of the <hi>Portugals</hi> coming that way, the reſt of the Fleet of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Dutch</hi> being thus weakned by the default of the four <hi>Dutch</hi> ſhips aforeſaid; the faireſt opportunity that ever hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned either before or ſince the joyning of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Dutch</hi> Companies, or is ever likely to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer it ſelf in the future, was loſt and utterly defeated. By this it appeareth, what cauſe the <hi>Dutch</hi> have to complain of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> for deſerting the action of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, and what reaſon and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement the <hi>Engliſh</hi> have to continue the joynt action and charge with thoſe that uſe ſo lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ſincerity, ever contriving the common actions and charge to their private advantage; that when the joint forces are imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to give the enemy work in one
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:169753:72"/>part, they (the <hi>Hollanders</hi>) might with eaſe oppreſs them in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and appropriate the whole benefit to themſelves.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="D"/> The next ſuſpicion that this au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor gathereth, is from the inſole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of the <hi>Ternatans</hi> of <hi>Amboyna,</hi> dwelling at <hi>Lobo</hi> and <hi>Cambello,</hi> &amp; thereabouts; who (as this Author ſaith) preſumed now beyond for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer example, to outrage the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of the <hi>Dutch,</hi> ſlaying them, &amp; carrying them away for ſlaves, yea, burning two of their houſes, one at <hi>Lobo,</hi> and another at <hi>Manichels:</hi> for which, when the Governour went out with a Fleet to crave ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and reparation, he was braved by the <hi>Ternatans</hi> with a ſtronger Fleet than his own; yea, they threatned to come with an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred <hi>Curricurries</hi> againſt <hi>Amboyna.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This dealing of the Author is like the former about the Treaty of peace with the <hi>Tedorians,</hi> and truce with the <hi>Spaniards.</hi> For when the Governour of <hi>Amboyna</hi> ſet forth the laſt Fleet of <hi>Curricur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> before the apprehenſion of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> he ſtood in good tearms with the <hi>Ternatans</hi> at <hi>Lobos</hi>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:169753:73"/>neither of the Factories here mentioned, being then burnt or injured. The Governour then went onely, according to his yearly cuſtom, to viſit the skirts and out-parts of <hi>Amboyna,</hi> and had no affront offered him. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that, upon occaſion of a Slave of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> that ran away, and being afterwards laid hold on, was reſcued by a reputed holy man of or near that part; the <hi>Engliſh</hi> craved aſſiſtance of the <hi>Dutch</hi> Governour, who did his beſt, but was therein abuſed by thoſe of <hi>Lobo;</hi> and not onely ſome of his men outraged, but the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Factor M. <hi>Beomont</hi> (to whom this Slave belonged) was way-laid by the people of the ſaid holy man: and in ſtead of him, one of the ſervants of the <hi>Dutch</hi> was ſlain between <hi>Cambello</hi> and <hi>Lobo.</hi> The next day alſo, was <hi>Beo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mont</hi> himſelf aſſailed, and ſhot in the hand by the ſame holy mans people, who alſo a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore did their beſt to kill <hi>William Grigs,</hi> another of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Factours, that finding the ſaid Slave at <hi>Lobo,</hi> laid hold on him
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:169753:73"/>there. Upon this occaſion, both the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Dutch</hi> left their Factorie at <hi>Lobo,</hi> which was ſhortly after burnt by thoſe <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natans.</hi> That other, touching the burning of the Factorie at <hi>Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chels,</hi> is more groſſely applied than the former; for that Factorie was burnt after the <hi>Engliſh</hi> were ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended: beſides that, this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour diſſembleth that there was a vehement and common ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion at <hi>Amboyna,</hi> that this Factory at <hi>Manichels</hi> was burnt, not by the <hi>Ternatans,</hi> but by the <hi>Dutch</hi> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor himſelf, who, being there alone, was ſaid to have firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed away the goods of the <hi>Dutch</hi> and the <hi>Engliſh</hi> there for his own uſe, and then to have burnt the Factorie; laying the fact upon the <hi>Ternatans.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>After this ended, the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour of <hi>Amboyna</hi> made out a Fleet of <hi>Curricurries,</hi> to procure reparation of thoſe exceſſes; and therein not going ſo ſtrong as he might, was braved by thoſe <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natanes</hi> of <hi>Amboyna.</hi> But this was after the apprehenſion and execution of the Engliſh; and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:169753:74"/>ſo is as honeſtly applied to move ſuſpicion in this place, as the joynt quarrel of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Dutch</hi> with thoſe of <hi>Lobo,</hi> beginning up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on occaſion of the Engliſh, and as the burning of the Factorie at <hi>Manichels,</hi> done after the <hi>Engliſh</hi> were apprehended and impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. As for the threats of the <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natans</hi> here mentioned, that they would come with 100. <hi>Curricur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> againſt <hi>Amboyna,</hi> it is (for ought any of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> ever heard) a meer fiction; at moſt, it was a vain bragge, and ſuch as could not affright the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, that knoweth well that the <hi>Ternatans</hi> have no gun-powder, nor other proviſions for ſuch an exploit; and yet are far behind the Governour of <hi>Amboyna</hi> for number of <hi>Curricurries,</hi> beſides the <hi>Dutch</hi> ſhips and Caffles.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="E"/> The next cauſe of ſuſpicion, this Authour makes to be an idle report in the Eaſt parts beyond <hi>Banda</hi> (uncertain which, or by whom) that the <hi>Hollanders</hi> were already quit of their Caſtle at <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boyna.</hi> A poor prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, &amp; not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be anſwered; yet ſtill further
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:169753:74"/>diſcovering what penurie of good matter this author had, that he was fain to borrow ſuch crazie ſtuffe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="F"/> But the laſt, and that which alone is expreſly applyed to the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> is, That about this time the <hi>Dutch</hi> underſtood, that thoſe of <hi>Lobo</hi> and <hi>Cambello</hi> held great and ſecret correſpondence with the <hi>Engliſh.</hi> How did the <hi>Dutch</hi> underſtand this? or why doth not this Authour expreſs the particular proof, in a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſo pertinent? It is true, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> had their Factories at <hi>Lobo</hi> and <hi>Cambello;</hi> but in the ſame houſes with the <hi>Dutch;</hi> and for their joynt accompt, and had Traffick with the Countrey-people, as the <hi>Dutch</hi> had, but what ſecret correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence is this? or what danger to the <hi>Dutch?</hi> Was the burning of the Factories, which belonged to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> as well as to the <hi>Dutch,</hi> a note of good intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence between the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and the <hi>Imcendiaries?</hi> What was that for correſpondencie with thoſe of <hi>Lobo,</hi> when at one time they way-laied M. <hi>Beomont</hi> to kill him,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:169753:75"/>and at another time ſhot him in the hand with an Arrow, offered to kill <hi>Williams Grigs,</hi> and from time to time abuſed and outra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged our People, equally with, and as the <hi>Dutch?</hi> further, our Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple as well as the <hi>Dutch,</hi> had now diſſolved their Factorie at <hi>Lobo,</hi> and were come all thence. What Letters or Meſſages did they ever ſend thither after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards? or how, and by what means maintained they this cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondence? Yet this was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, ſaith this Relation. How underſtood? Perhaps by the Governours dreams: for that (as he afterwards told M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, Hill,</hi> and <hi>Cartwright,</hi> that came thither from <hi>Banda</hi>) was a motive to him to examin the firſt <hi>Japon,</hi> which was the beginning of the whole proceſs.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="G"/> The Authour having thus quit himſelf in this preface, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth to the matter it ſelf, firſt ſetting down the occaſion and manner of the discoverie of this pretended plot, and then the confeſſions of the <hi>Japons</hi> and of the <hi>Engliſh:</hi> but he maketh no
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:169753:75"/>mention of any torture uſed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Japons</hi> that firſt confeſſed, nor of any other <hi>indicium</hi> or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption to torture or examin that <hi>Japon;</hi> but onely his curious queſtioning, touching the ſetting and changing of the Watch, and of the number of the Souldiers in the Caſtle: which, what ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient <hi>indicium</hi> and cauſe it was to torture a Souldier of their own, that ſerving them, had rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to deſire to underſtand the courſe of their Watches, and the ſtrength of the aid he might ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect, if any ſudden attempt ſhould happen in his quarter; is eaſily to be judged. And how this poor man, and the reſt of his Countrey-men were tortured, appeareth in the Engliſh relation. Here alſo is concealed, by what manner and kind of queſtions, this and the other <hi>Japons</hi> were led along in their confeſſions, to make up the plot juſt as the <hi>Dutch</hi> had deviſed it: as alſo, what o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther anſwers they made, before they were thus directed. That they, and the <hi>Engliſh</hi> both, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed what the <hi>Dutch</hi> would
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:169753:76"/>have them, is no doubt nor won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, being ſo tormented and fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with torture; <hi>etiam innocentes cogit mentiri dolor,</hi> But what like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyhood or poſſibilitie there is of the truth of their confeſſions (if yet they confeſſed, as is here re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated) may appear by that which hath been alreadie diſcourſed in this point, towards the end of the Engliſh Relation, which for bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vities ſake is here forborn to be repeated: yet ſome circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which the <hi>Dutch</hi> Relation hath more than the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve here to be examined. And firſt, that of <hi>Abel Price</hi> the Engliſh Barber, who is made the meſſenger and negotiator of this practice with the <hi>Japons.</hi> It is true, that he (and he alone of all the Engliſh) had ſome kind of converſation with ſome of the <hi>Japons,</hi> that is, he would dice and drink with them, as he likewiſe did with other Blacks, and with the <hi>Dutch</hi> alſo. But is it credible, that Mr. <hi>Towerſon</hi> would com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit any thing of moment, nay, ſo dangerous a matter as this to a drunken debauched ſot, who
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:169753:76"/>alſo (as the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> that were there, conſtantly report) threatned to cut his, the ſaid <hi>Towerſon's</hi> throat, for that he had puniſhed him for his misdemeanours? Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, this Relation maketh this <hi>Abel Price</hi> confeſs, that all the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Merchants in the out-Factories, were privy and acceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie to this pretended treaſon: Yet the Governour and Fiſcal in in their own proceſs found <hi>John Powel, Ephraim Ramſey,</hi> and two other, guiltleſs.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="H"/> After <hi>Price</hi> his confeſſion, he ſets down the general ſubſtance of all the confeſſions in one hody; where firſt having aſſigned M. <hi>Towerſon</hi> a preface to the reſt, to induce them to the exploit, he tells us; that they made doubt of the point of poſſibility, (as well they might) knowing the weakneſs of their own part &amp; impregnable ſtrength of the <hi>Dutch,</hi> in compariſon of theirs: for ſatisfaction of which their doubt, he ſaith, M. <hi>Towerſon</hi> told him that he had already won the <hi>Japons</hi> within the Caſtle to his purpoſe, and that he would at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt this matter; not when the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:169753:77"/>
                     <hi>Dutch</hi> were at their full ſtrength, and the <hi>Engliſh</hi> at the weakeſt, but would expect till the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour ſhould be ſomewhere abroad upon ſome exploit, and ſome <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> Ships, or Ship at leaſt, at <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boyna;</hi> the people whereof he would uſe in the enterprize: Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe he would ſend for the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors and ſlaves of the other Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctories, and ſhould have a ſupply from the <hi>Ternatans</hi> of <hi>Lobo,</hi> of certain <hi>Curricurries,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> Here he hath inrolled a goodly army for this action; but let us ſee the manner how they ſhould have executed their exploit: and firſt for the <hi>Japons</hi> in the Caſtle, we muſt believe, if this Authour or his voucher ſay true, that Maſter <hi>Towerſon</hi> had acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thoſe, and won them to his plot, before he had imparted it to his own Countrey-men the <hi>Engliſh.</hi> And yet in the acts of the proceſs, <hi>Emanuel Tomſon</hi> is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded to have confeſſed, that 8. dayes after the conſultation, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Towerſon</hi> told him, that he had then ſent out <hi>Johnſon</hi> and <hi>Price</hi> to treat with the <hi>Japons,</hi> and win
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:169753:77"/>their conſent to this enterprize. But what ſhould theſe (being all but ten) have done? Marrie (ſaith the relation by and by) Mr. <hi>Tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erſon</hi> had ordeined, that eight of them ſhould have been beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, by two in a company, upon the four points of the Caſtle, to kill all thoſe that would reſiſt them, and to take the reſt Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. It muſt be (therefore) here imagined, that the <hi>Dutch</hi> and their Mardikers in their Caſtle, being three or four hundred, would ſcorn to take the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of ſending fortie or fiftie; much more of an entire compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to any point of the Caſtle, but would combate with the <hi>Japons</hi> at even hand by two at a time, and ſo give the <hi>Japons</hi> leave and reſpite to kill or take them by two and by two. A ſweet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, and ſuch a ſervice as per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps hath been ſometimes repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented upon a ſtage, but never act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in ſurpriſe of a Caſtle in good earneſt.</p>
                  <p>Thus we ſee how eight of the <hi>Japons</hi> were to be imployed; what ſhould the other two have
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:169753:78"/>done? forſooth they ſhould have waited in the great chamber to murder the Governour. Yea, but this relation told us yer while, that this plot ſhould have been executed when the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour was abroad upon ſome acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. How then ſhould theſe two <hi>Japons</hi> have killed him in the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, at the ſame time? But we ſee how all the <hi>Japons</hi> (that is) all the pretended party of the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> within the Caſtle, ſhould have been occupied. Who ſhould have opened the gates to the Engliſh, and their other aids? who ſhould have killed the Court of guard at the Gate? Theſe parts were left for them that were without; therefore let us take a review of them, what they were. The Relation muſtereth them to be fourteen Engliſh, whereof ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven were Merchants; one Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard of the houſe, one Tailor, and one Barber, to dreſs the wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, beſides God knows how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Engliſh ſhippers, Slaves, and <hi>Ternatans:</hi> Firſt, for the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Merchants, of what dexte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie they are to take Forts, is
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:169753:78"/>eaſily judged; and in all the <hi>Engliſh</hi> houſe, when it was ſeized by the <hi>Dutch,</hi> upon this pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Treaſon, the whole Proviſion was but three Swords, two Hand-guns, and about half a pound of Powder. Yea, but the <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſhip or ſhips would have brought both fitter men and better proviſion. But how knew Maſter <hi>Towerſon</hi> that thoſe of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſhips, when they came, would joyn with him in this work, being ſo contrary to the Treaty, and it ſelf ſo danger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous? or why did he not ſtay the opening of the Plot till this ſhip or ſhips were come, that he might ſwear the ſhippers alſo, or at leaſt the chief Officers amongſt them, and take their advice? Is it poſſible that Maſter <hi>Tower<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> was ſo ſlight, as to open his plot to all the <hi>Engliſh</hi> at <hi>Amboy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> yea, to the Tailor and Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, ſo long before it was to be put in execution, and before he knew the minds of his chiefeſt aſſiſtants, of whoſe arrival he was ſo uncertain? Yea, but he was ſure of the Slaves of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi>
                     <pb n="24" facs="tcp:169753:79"/>and of the <hi>Ternatans</hi> of <hi>Lobo,</hi> with their <hi>Curricurries in quem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libet eventum.</hi> This indeed is the remainder of the Army; let us view them. The Slaves were, in all the Engliſh Factories, juſt ſix in number, and all boys: The <hi>Ternatans</hi> were Enemies as well to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> as to the <hi>Dutch,</hi> as is before ſhewed in anſwer to the Preface. When were they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled? how cometh it, that in all the examinations of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> this point was not ſifted, and ſomewhat confeſſed of it amidſt ſo many Tortures? There is no confeſſion thereof in all the examinations; and M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
                     <hi>Tower<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> in his expreſly denied it, and was preſſed no further. The truth is, the Governour and Fiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal of <hi>Amboyna</hi> knew, that what ever had been confeſſed in this point, would not have been believed by their own People there; who knew well enough, that the firſt beginning of this breach between the <hi>Dutch</hi> and <hi>Ternatans</hi> of <hi>Lobo,</hi> was about the Slave of the Engliſh: and the outrages thereupon following,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:169753:79"/>were done upon the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> as well as upon the <hi>Dutch.</hi> Yet this Authour ſeems to hope that that may be believed here in <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope,</hi> which had no colour at <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boyna.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="K"/> Concerning the time of exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting this plot, it was not (as the Relation ſaith) yet prefixed, but left to the next meeting of the Conſpiratours, which ſhould be ſhortly holden, when <hi>Gabriel Towerſon</hi> had prepared all things, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Here was certainly a hot practice of Treaſon, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be tearmed by this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour, An horrible conſpiracie. They met together on New years day, and plotted as is before re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated: and now it was the five, and twentieth of <hi>February,</hi> and not onely nothing done all this <hi>Interim,</hi> but not ſo much as a new conſultation. But this (for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth) is the body and ſubſtance of the unanimous confeſſion of all the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> by themſelves ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verally ſubſcribed. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="L"/> In the next place the Authour relateth ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what ſingular in M. <hi>Towerſon</hi>'s confeſſion; as that he ſaid, he
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:169753:80"/>was moved to this fact by hope and deſire of honour and profit: and being demanded from whom he attended this honour, and for whom he meant to hold the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, his anſwer was, That if he could have compaſſed his project, he would forthwith have given advertiſement thereof to the reſt of his Nation at <hi>Jaccatra</hi> (which now they have chriſtened <hi>Bata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>via,</hi>) and have craved their aid: which if they had yielded to him, then he would have held the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle for the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Company; and if not, then he would have kept it for himſelf, and have uſed means to have agreed with the <hi>Indians;</hi> and ſo, by one means or other, would have compaſſed the enterprize.</p>
                  <p>Here firſt is to be obſerved, that he would not (as this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour makes him ſpeak) have ſent for aid to <hi>Jaccatra,</hi> until he were firſt Maſter of the Caſtle; and yet in the general confeſſion before, it is ſaid, he would attend the coming of ſome <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſhips or ſhip, before he would adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture upon the Caſtle. Next, let the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:169753:80"/>ambiguous and alternative reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, here ſaid to be confeſſed by Maſter <hi>Towerſon,</hi> be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered in both the parts thereof, and it will appear, that no man in his wits would have any ſuch conceit as is here pretended. What hope could Maſter <hi>Tower<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> have, that the Preſident and <hi>Engliſh</hi> Councel at <hi>Jaccatra,</hi> li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving under command of the <hi>Dutch</hi> Fort there, and altogether Subject to the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> durſt join in any ſuch action, thereby to give occaſion to the <hi>Hollan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> to arreſt, torture and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn them of Treaſon? Maſter <hi>Towerſon</hi> knew well enough, that about ſix Moneths before, the General of the <hi>Dutch</hi> at <hi>Jacca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra,</hi> had caught at a very ſlight occaſion to entrap the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Preſident there: who having ſent out two of his people in the night to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Cow-houſe, to ſee what watch the <hi>Blacks</hi> in their ſervice kept over their Cattel; the ſaid two <hi>Engliſh</hi> were appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended by the <hi>Dutch</hi> Souldiers, kept in priſon ſeven dayes, and charged, that they had ſaid, that
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:169753:81"/>they went the Round: and one of them, being laſt examined, was told by the <hi>Balieu</hi> (the Officer of the <hi>Dutch</hi> in Criminal cauſes) that his fellow had confeſſed, that they had ſaid they went the Round, and that by the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Preſidents Commiſſion; and if he would not confeſs the ſame, he ſhould be tortured: but the fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, being conſtant in the truth, came off at laſt without torture, yet this was <hi>Item</hi> enough to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Preſident and Councel, how the intent of the <hi>Dutch</hi> was to entrap them upon the leaſt oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion: and this, and other day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly captious dealings of the <hi>Dutch</hi> at <hi>Jaccatra,</hi> which were too long here to recite, were all advertiſed from time to time to M. <hi>Tower<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> who therefore was ſure he could expect no aſſiſtance from them, that were themſelves in in ſuch a predicament. The other part of Mr <hi>Towerſon</hi>'s reſolution is ſaid to have been, To keep the Caſtle for himſelf, and to agree with the <hi>Indians,</hi> in default of help from the <hi>Engliſh.</hi> This is yet more improbable than the former.
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:169753:81"/>Were the <hi>Portugals</hi> and <hi>Indians</hi> not able to keep out the <hi>Dutch</hi> from <hi>Amboyna,</hi> when they had no footing there; and ſhall Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>Towerſon,</hi> with twenty or thirty <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Japons,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſhip or Pinnace, be able, with the help onely of the poor naked <hi>Indians,</hi> to drive them out, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving already three Caſtles in the Iſlands of <hi>Amboyna,</hi> and at <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bello</hi> hard by, all well furniſhed with men and proviſion, beſides their power of ſhipping, which makes them ſtile themſelves Lords of the Sea? And yet how could Maſter <hi>Towerſon</hi> hope to win the <hi>Amboynezes</hi> (the <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landers</hi> ſworn Subjects) to his ſide? He might rather aſſure him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, that after he had maſtered the <hi>Hollanders</hi> (if yet that muſt be believed to be poſſible) the <hi>Amboynezes</hi> would have ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized him, and caſt him out (being ſo weakly provided to ſtand of himſelf,) that ſo they might utterly free themſelve fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their ſervitude. Here alſo muſt be remembred, that this Authori him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in his preamble ſaith, that
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:169753:82"/>the <hi>Indians</hi> themſelves durſt not undertake any ſuch great deſign (as he there feineth) againſt the State of <hi>Amboyna,</hi> without ſome great aid of ſome Nation of Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope, either of <hi>Spaniards, Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gals,</hi> or ſome other. Whereby is not onely confeſſed, how weak the <hi>Indians</hi> of themſelves are; but withall it followeth, how ſmall hope Mr. <hi>Towerſon</hi> might have, being deſerted of his own Nation (as here the caſe is put,) to hold the Caſtle for himſelf by the help of thoſe <hi>Indians,</hi> if yet he could once have won it. In a word; they that know the power of the <hi>Hollanders</hi> in <hi>Amboyna</hi> and thereabouts, and the weakenſs of the poor <hi>Indians</hi> there, will judge this conceit of Maſter <hi>Towerſon</hi>'s (to keep the Caſtle for himſelf) to be a mad plot; and for which, Maſter <hi>Tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erſon</hi> ſhould rather have been ſent to Bedlam, or the <hi>Dullen Kiſt</hi> (as the <hi>Dutch</hi> call it,) than to the Gallows. </p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="M"/> But this Authour hath one vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarie confeſſion, upon which he taketh ſpecial hold; to wit,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:169753:82"/>that Maſter <hi>Towerſon,</hi> after his examination was finiſhed, being expoſtulated withall by the <hi>Dutch</hi> Governour, and demanded whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this ſhould have been the recompenſe of his (the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours) manifold courteſies to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him; anſwered with a deep ſigh, Oh! were this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter now to do, it ſhould never be done. <hi>This voluntarie confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and penitent acknowledgement, ſaith this Authour, was made the ninth of March, being the day when the execution was to be done: but the examination of</hi> Tower<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon <hi>was ended the eight and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth of February, ſo many dayes before.</hi> But how ſhall we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve this? Forſooth, he hath it out of the Acts of the Proceſs of <hi>Amboyna.</hi> Yea, but in theſe Acts are omitted many material paſſages of theſe examinations, as is already ſhewed: why may they not then be guiltie of addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as well as of ſuch mutilation and omiſſion? But let us peruſe the words of the Act it ſelf, which are theſe:</p>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:169753:83"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>WE whoſe names are hereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſubſcribed, to declare upon our troth, in ſtead of an oath, that</hi> Gabriel Towerſon, <hi>after that he had been already examined touching his ſaid offence, and that the Worſhipfull Governour</hi> Van Speult <hi>had expoſtulated with him thereupon, asking him whether this ſhould have been the recompenſe of his courteſies from time to time ſhewed unto him, the ſaid</hi> Tower<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: <hi>thereupon he, the ſaid</hi> Tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erſon, <hi>with a deep ſigh anſwered him, and ſaid, Oh! if this were to be begun again, it ſhould never be done.</hi> Actum <hi>this ninth of March, in the Caſtle of</hi> Amboyna, <hi>and ſubſigned.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <list>
                     <item>Harman van Speult.</item>
                     <item>Haurence de Maerſchalck.</item>
                     <item>Clement Kerſſe boom.</item>
                     <item>Harman Cray-vanger.</item>
                     <item>Peter van Zanten.</item>
                     <item>Leonart Clock.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>Thus we ſee the Act it ſelf, and this pretended voluntarie confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Towerſon;</hi> which is not delivered upon the credit of
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:169753:83"/>the Court or Councel at <hi>Amboy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi> (and yet how ſmall that is, is before ſhewed) but upon the Atteſtation or Affidavit of the Governour and five others, the principal actors in this bloudy Tragedie: And this not upon their Oath, but upon their troth, or honeſt word (forſooth) in ſtead of an Oath. The time when theſe words were uttered by Mr. <hi>Tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erſon,</hi> is not deſcribed by the day when he ſpake them, but onely by the precedent Act of his exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination. And yet the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of time is not onely an uſual and cuſtomrie ſolemnity, and requiſite in all ſuch Atteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; but alſo in a buſineſs of this nature altogether neceſſarie: as likewiſe in this caſe, that of the place was. For if theſe words were ſpoken in the place of Torture, or incontinently after the examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ended, they are by their own Law, eſteemed no more volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, than the confeſſion upon the Rack it ſelf. Neither yet doth this Atteſtation affirm, that this confeſſion was voluntarie. But this Authour, unconſcionably
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:169753:84"/>reporting the date of the Atte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation, for the time of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, collects it to be volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie, becauſe (as he ſaith) it was made the ninth of March, being ſo many dayes after his examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which was taken the 28. of February. Can a man atteſt nothing but what was done up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the very day when he maketh Affidavit? The Atteſtation ſaith, that theſe words were ſpoken by M. <hi>Towerſon,</hi> after he had been already examined. Why may not that have been rather upon the very day of his examination, than upon the day when this Act was entred; if yet he ever ſpake any ſuch words, or meant them, as he is here interpreted? the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie whereof is the more probable by all the circumſtances of this buſineſs, truely ſet down in the Relation of the <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But in that this Author makes ſo much of this poor circumſtance, of M. <hi>Towerſons</hi> profeſſion of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row for what was done, naming it a voluntary confeſſion; it is plain how deſtitute he was of volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie confeſſions, and of all true and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:169753:84"/>concluding circumſtances. What? was there not a Letter or other Paper, to be found in all the Cheſts and Boxes of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> ſo ſuddenly ſeiſed at <hi>Amboyna, Larica, Hitto,</hi> and <hi>Cambello,</hi> to diſcover this treaſon? nor amongſt ſo many complices of diverſe Nations, a falſe brother to betray the reſt, and to accuſe them vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarily; but the proceſs muſt begin with the Torture, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> and the Heathens confeſſion upon Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, be ſufficient to bring Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians to Torture, the debauched and notoriouſly infamous perſons (ſuch as <hi>Prive</hi> was) to draw tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture upon the ſober, orderly, and unſtained? And yet this Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion it ſelf confeſſeth, that <hi>Price's</hi> confeſſion was drawn from him by the Examiners ſpecifying of place, perſon and time unto him. Certainly one of their own Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion had reaſon to advice, that more Advocates might be ſent over to the <hi>Indies,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration to the Lords States, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hing the govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Majores.</note> to aid the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed, to make a legal anſwer: For, ſaith he, they go to work there ſo villanouſly and murther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, that the bloud of the poor
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:169753:85"/>people crieth to heaven for ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance.</p>
                  <p>But why have we no particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar of any mans confeſſion, but this of <hi>Price,</hi> and M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Towerſon,</hi> and all the reſt blended together in one body? Did none of all the reſt go farther than his fellows, or confeſs more than they? Where is <hi>Sharrocks</hi> confeſſion, that he was at <hi>Amboyna</hi> upon New-years day, when ten or twelve of the <hi>Dutch</hi> themſelves witneſſed he was at <hi>Hitto?</hi> Where is his confeſſion of <hi>Clarks</hi> plot to go to <hi>Maccaſſar,</hi> to deal with the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards</hi> there, to come and rob the ſamll Factories? Where is <hi>Collins</hi> confeſſion of another plot, about two Moneths and a half before his examination, under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken by <hi>Tomſon, Johnſon, Price, Brown, Fardo,</hi> and himſelf? Where be the leading Interrogatories, that directed them to the accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation framed by the <hi>Dutch,</hi> leſt otherwiſe there had been as many ſeveral Treaſons confeſſed, as perſons examined? Not a word of all this, nor of a great deal more of this kind, which is here
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:169753:85"/>in <hi>England</hi> proved by the oath of ſix credible perſons, to have paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the examinations. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by appeareth, how faithfully the <hi>Dutch</hi> at <hi>Amboyna</hi> have entered the Acts of this proceſs. Well, at laſt he concludes the Narration of the confeſſions, with the ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming up of the number and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the parties, that had thus confeſſed; which, he ſaith, were ten <hi>Japons</hi> fourteen <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and the <hi>Neatherlandiſh Marnicho,</hi> or Captain of the Slaves By which laſt words, he would give the Reader occaſion to think, that the fact was ſo clear, and their own proceeding ſo even and juſt, that they had executed one of their own <hi>Neatherlanders</hi> for it. Which how true it is, is already declared in the concluſion of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Relation. The truth is, this Captain of the Slaves was of the <hi>Portugal</hi> race, and born in <hi>Bengala.</hi> His very name, <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin Perez,</hi> ſheweth, he was no <hi>Neatherlander.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Having thus finiſhed this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, this Authour proceedeth to a diſputation: and taking no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:169753:86"/>of ſome aſperſions in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> caſt upon theſe proceedings at <hi>Amboyna,</hi> he divideth them into two heads; the one, that the proceſs was without its due formalitie; the other, that there was exceſs and extremitie uſed againſt the Conſpiratours. For the point of formalitie, he firſt taketh great pains to prove, that the formalities of proceſs in <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boyna,</hi> are not therefore unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, becauſe they agree not with our form in <hi>England.</hi> Which labour he might have ſpared: for no wiſe man will denie him this point. And ſuch as ſhall be ſo ignorant as to blame the <hi>Dutch</hi> for varying from us herein, were not worthy the anſwering. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withall alſo he deduceth the Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of the Lords States General to the Sovereignty of <hi>Amboyna;</hi> and ſo the Governour of <hi>Amboy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na'es</hi> Juriſdiction, in cauſes as well Criminal as Civil, to be rightly grounded. Thence he concludes, that the <hi>Japons</hi> being ſworn ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants to the <hi>Dutch,</hi> and in their pay, were Subject to the Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction of the <hi>Dutch</hi> Governour.
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:169753:86"/>Then he telleth us, that the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour, and complices of murther and treaſon, are by the Laws of all Nations to be puniſhed with death; all which points may be granted him without any preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice to the cauſe of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> in this queſtion.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="O"/> At laſt he comes in particular to their caſe, and affirms, that the chief of the Engliſh there might not apprehend the <hi>Engliſh</hi> complices of this conſpiracie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe themſelves were complices of the fact. All which alſo may be granted in this point of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion, and ſafe cuſtodie: but how it may proceed alſo in the point of cogniſance, ſhall be anon in due place examined.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="P"/> In the mean time, this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour, to make the point of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion clear beyond excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſaith, that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> were not apprehended upon the firſt ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, when yet there was evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and <hi>indicia</hi> ſufficient to it; but after the examination of all the <hi>Japons</hi> and their joynt confeſſion, that the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> whom they ſpecified by name
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:169753:87"/>and ſurname, had moved and hired them to this treaſon: yea, not until <hi>Abel Price</hi> had alſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed as much, and that all the <hi>Engliſh</hi> in the out-Factories were privy thereunto. For anſwer here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, that muſt be repeated which hath been upon other occaſions before alleadged; that the firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the proceſs, was by the Torture, there being no ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient evidence or <hi>indicium</hi> to Torture the <hi>Japon,</hi> that onely ſought to enform himſelf of the courſe of the Watch, and of the ſtrength of the Caſtle, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in himſelf was a Souldier: and ſo the whole <hi>Series</hi> of the exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation proceeding from the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of one Tortured perſon, to apprehend and Torture an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, without other evidence; though it brought forth more confeſſions, and thoſe with name and ſurname, and other circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, according as the Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatories (or rather directories) of the Governour and Fiſcal led the priſoners, was wholly againſt the form and rule of all Laws of Tortures.</p>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:169753:87"/>
                  <q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Scilicet in fabrica ſi pravae eſt regula prima,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Caetera mendoſe fieri, atque obſtipa neceſſe eſt.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
                  <p>But here muſt be anſwered an objection that may be made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this, from another part of this relation, that is, that ſome of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> confeſſed without or before Torture; yea, this <hi>Price</hi> here mentioned, was either not Tortured at all, or very lightly. Yea, but he was ſhewed the Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured bodies of the poor <hi>Japons,</hi> martyred with fire and water, and told, that unleſs he would confeſs that, which they told him they had firſt confeſſed, he ſhould be Tortured as ill, or worſe than they. This fear of Torture is by their own Law, equalled to the Torture it ſelf, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the confeſſion thereupon made no better <hi>indicium</hi> or evidence to bring another man to the Torture, than the confeſſion made upon the Rack it ſelf. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, it muſt be here remembred, that the very matter of <hi>Price</hi> his confeſſion here mentioned, to wit, that all the <hi>Engliſh</hi>
                     <pb n="42" facs="tcp:169753:88"/>Merchants of the out-Facto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, were privy to the pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed treaſon; was reſuted by the proceſs of the <hi>Dutch</hi> themſelves, that found <hi>Powel, Ramſey,</hi> and two others of thoſe Factories guiltleſs.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Q"/> Next, this Authour taketh notice of an objection made in <hi>England</hi> againſt the Juriſdiction of the <hi>Dutch</hi> Governour, and his Councel at <hi>Amboyna,</hi> over the <hi>Engliſh</hi> there; becauſe this power is, by the Treatie of the year 1619. diſpoſed of, and agreed to conſiſt in the Councel of defence of both Nations at <hi>Jaccatra.</hi> For information in which point this Authour ſaith, he hath peruſed over all the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Articles of the ſaid Treatie, and findeth in the 23. Article, that the Fortreſſes were to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main in the hands of them that then poſſeſſed them; and in the thirteenth, fourteenth, and fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth, that the Councel of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence hath no other power, but onely over the Fleet of defence, over the commerce, and finally, to tax the charges of maintenance
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:169753:88"/>of the Forts: But he could not ſee the thirtieth Article; which orders, that all diſputes that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be decided by the Councel of defence, ſhould be remitted into <hi>Europe;</hi> firſt, to the two com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies there, and in default of their agreement, to the King and States. Why then was not this diſpute ſo proceeded in? There is nothing in the former Articles, to limit the Councel of defence; and this general Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle appeareth to be added by way of ampliation, to provide for that which was not particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly and expreſly cared for in the former. Which is moſt plain by the words of the expla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation upon this thirtieth Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, agreed upon at the firſt, and ſubſcribed by the Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners on both ſides, Anno 1619. where this courſe of proceeding is expreſly directed, not onely in diſputes about the meaning of the Articles, but alſo about any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther matter hapning in their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon aboad. Since which alſo the Kings Majeſtie hath, upon a ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler occaſion, than the life of his
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:169753:89"/>Subjects, clearly declared himſelf in the point of Sovereignrie; That both Nations in the <hi>Indies</hi> ſhould wholly lay aſide all pretence thereof. Which Declaration was ſent to the Lords States General, and by them accepted before this bloudie butcherie was executed. But if it were granted, that the <hi>Hollanders</hi> are abſolute Lords of their partners, the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> in thoſe parts, without reſpect to the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, yet at leaſt the <hi>Hollanders</hi> in <hi>Amboyna</hi> are bound to obſerve the Laws of the united Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; for ſo ſaith this Authour himſelf. Do theſe allow to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin the proceſs at the torture, and to bring perſons of honeſt fame to the rack, upon others confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on made in the torture? Do their Laws allow of the leading inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatories above mentioned to direct the priſoner what to ſay, to avoid the torture? Where, in the United Provinces, is that drown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with water in uſe? or the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture with fire, uſed to <hi>Johnſon, Tompſan,</hi> and <hi>Clark?</hi> or eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the ſplitting of their toes, and launcing of the breaſt, and put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:169753:89"/>in Gun-pouder, and then firing the ſame, whereby the body is not left intire, neither for innocencie, nor execution? <hi>Clark</hi> and <hi>Tomſon</hi> were both fain to be carried to their execution, though they were tortured many days before.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, their confeſſions were contradictorie, apparently falſe. and of things impoſſible to be done, much leſs practiſed before by the ſaid parties; and therefore ought not by their law to have been believed, nor the priſoners to have been condemned thereupon, without other ſufficient <hi>indicia</hi> or evidence beſides.</p>
                  <p>In the laſt place, this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour handleth the exceſs of torture whereof (he taketh notice) there is much com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint in <hi>England;</hi> and ſaith, That the Lords States Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral take great care to inform themſelves of all the paſſages of this buſineſs, and to that end have deſired to ſee all the Letters, Pieces, and Papers that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern this proceſſe: by which it appeareth not, that there was
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:169753:90"/>any cruel torture uſed. But ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the Acts make no mention of them; is it any marvel that the Authours of this murtherous and tyrannous proceſs, being them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the perſons that alſo form<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Acts, would omit thoſe things that made againſt them? It is to be preſumed alſo, that the Acts kept by their people at <hi>Polo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way</hi> in <hi>Banda,</hi> have omitted many things of their proceſs, againſt the poor <hi>Polaroons,</hi> whom in <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt</hi> 1622, being about 6 months before this execution of the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh,</hi> their Governour there uſed in like ſort, as the Governour of <hi>Amboyna</hi> did the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and gave him a Model and precedent of this proceſs; which it will not be amiſs to relate briefly, becauſe this Authour, in the next place alleadgeth the mercifull diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>Netherlands</hi> Nation in general; to inferr thence, that it is therefore unlikely, that their Governour at <hi>Amboyna</hi> was ſo cruel as is reported in <hi>England.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Polaroon,</hi> one of the Iſlands of <hi>Banda,</hi> was in poſſeſſion of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> at the time of the Treatie,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:169753:90"/>
                     <hi>Anno</hi> 1619, and by the agreement was to remain theirs. After the Treatie came to the <hi>Indies,</hi> the <hi>Hollanders</hi> forbare the publiſhing thereof in the Iſlands of <hi>Banda;</hi> untill they had taken <hi>Polaroon.</hi> But, knowing that it muſt be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored again, according to the Treatie, they firſt take all courſes to make the Iſland little or no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing worth: they demoliſh and deface the Building, transplant the Nutmeg-trees plucking them up by the roots, and carrying them into their own Iſlands of <hi>Nera</hi> and of <hi>Poloway,</hi> there to be planted for themſelves; and at laſt find a means to dispeople the Iſland, and to leave it ſo, as the <hi>Engliſh</hi> might make no uſe of it, worth their charge of keeping; and that upon this occaſion: There was a young man, the ſon of an <hi>Orankey,</hi> or a Gentleman in <hi>Polaroon,</hi> that had committed Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonie; for which by the Laws of his Countrey, he was to die. This fellow, to ſave his life, fled to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other Iſland of <hi>Banda,</hi> called <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finging,</hi> and there turned Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an: but quickly underſtanding,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:169753:91"/>that that would not make him ſafe from puniſhment, he went back ſecretly to his own countrey of <hi>Polaroon;</hi> and, having lurked there a few days, took his paſſage for <hi>Nera,</hi> another Iſland, where the <hi>Dutch</hi> have a Fort; and told the <hi>Dutch</hi> Governour, that the <hi>Orankeys</hi> of <hi>Polaroon</hi> had conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to Maſſacre the <hi>Dutch,</hi> as well at <hi>Polaroon,</hi> as at <hi>Poloway,</hi> with help of the people of <hi>Seran,</hi> that ſhould ſend over thirtie <hi>Curricur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> for that purpoſe. Immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately upon this <hi>indicium</hi> of this Malefactor, certain Prows, or Fiſher-boats of the <hi>Polaroons,</hi> that were fiſhing at <hi>Poloway,</hi> were ſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and the people made priſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. Command was ſent by the <hi>Dutch</hi> Governour to <hi>Polaroon;</hi> that the <hi>Orankeys</hi> ſhould come over to him, that there might be further inquiſition made of this matter. The Prieſt of the <hi>Pola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roons</hi> and ſeventie <hi>Orankes</hi> inſtantly took a Prow or ſmall veſſel of their own, and imbarked them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves for <hi>Poloway.</hi> As they were at ſea, and yet out of the ſight of the <hi>Dutch</hi> Caſtle, they were met
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:169753:91"/>by a Fiſher-boat of <hi>Bandanezes,</hi> and told, how all the reſt were apprehended; and that, if they went to <hi>Poloway,</hi> they were all but dead men. Nevertheleſs, the Prieſt and the reſt, although they had ſpace and means to have eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped to <hi>Seran</hi> and other places ſafe enough from the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> yet were ſo confident of their inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencie, that they would needs to <hi>Poloway</hi> to purge themſelves. Where, as ſoon as they were arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, they were inſtantly carried priſoners to the Caſtle: and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all the Governour, with a force of two hundred men, went pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently for <hi>Polaroon;</hi> whence he fetched all the reſt of the <hi>Orankeys,</hi> and brought them priſoners to the ſame Caſtle. As ſoon as they were come, they were preſently brought to the torture of water and fire, even in the ſame ſort as our people were afterwards at <hi>Amboyna;</hi> onely herein differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that of thoſe at <hi>Poloway,</hi> two were ſo tortured, that they died in their Tortures, the reſt, being one hundred and ſixtie two perſons, were all,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:169753:92"/>upon their own forced confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, condemned and executed. The Prieſt, when he came to the place of execution, ſpake theſe words in the <hi>Maliaian</hi> tongue: All ye, great and ſmall, rich and poor, black and white, look to it: we have committed no fault. And when he would have ſpoken more, he was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by the hands and feet, laid along, and cut in two by the middle with a ſword. Forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, the Governour cauſed the Wives, Children, and Slaves of thoſe of <hi>Polaroon,</hi> to be all car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried out of the Iſland, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtributed in other Iſlands ſubject to the <hi>Dutch;</hi> and ſo have made a clear Countrey for the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh,</hi> where they may both plant and gather themſelves, deſtitute of the help of any of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey people; without whom, neither the <hi>Engliſh</hi> nor <hi>Hollan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> can maintain their Trade in the <hi>Indies.</hi> And yet this is not here recited, to the end thereby to charge the <hi>Neatherlands</hi> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with thoſe cruel proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, but the perſons themſelves
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:169753:92"/>that have committed thoſe Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous Tyrannies: Who,
<note place="margin">Noot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wendich diſcourſe, <hi>printed An.</hi> 1622. <hi>under the name of</hi> Ymant <hi>van</hi> Waer mond.</note> if we ſhall believe an Authour of their own, are not of the beſt of that Nation. For the Majors (as this Authour ſayes) uſe the <hi>Indies</hi> as a <hi>Tucht-houſe</hi> or Bride-well, to manage their unruly and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrifty children and kindred; whom, when they cannot rule and order at home, they ſend to the <hi>Indies,</hi> where they are prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to Offices and places of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. Yea, ſaith he, they prefer ſuch to be Fiſcals there, as never ſaw Studie nor Law. So that it is no marvel, that ſuch perſons proceed not with that juſtice and moderation as is uſed generally in the <hi>Low-Countries,</hi> by the choice of the Nation there. And this agreeth well with the report of our Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants of credite, that came lately from <hi>Amboyna;</hi> who aver, that, excepting the Governour himſelf, who is well ſtept in years, of the reſt of the Councel there, as well the Fiſcal as others, there was ſcarce any that had hair on their faces, yea, that moſt
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:169753:93"/>of them are lewd drunken de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauched perſons; and yet muſt be Judges as well of our <hi>Engliſh,</hi> as the poor <hi>Indians</hi> there.</p>
                  <p>Now to return to this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thours proofs, that there was no exceſs uſed in the proceedings; at the laſt he taketh one Argument by way of compariſon, from the Law of <hi>England,</hi> to preſs men to death: which he ſaith, hath much more cruelty than their courſe of Torture, uſed by the <hi>Dutch</hi> in <hi>Amboyna,</hi> and is holden, as well by ſome Authours of our own Nation as others, for damnable. How pertinently is this matter of preſſing alleadged, for juſtifying of their Tortures, ſince no man in <hi>England</hi> is preſſed for not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing, which is the cauſe of Torture in <hi>Dutchland?</hi> But the cauſe why any is preſſed, is, for that he obſtinately refuſeth the Trial of his Countrey, and chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lengeth the Judges as incompe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, which the Law appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth him: which he doth (for the moſt part) to ſave his goods, which, but by that ordinarie courſe of Trial, cannot be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſcate.
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:169753:93"/>What is this to the point of confeſſion, for refuſal where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, the <hi>Dutch</hi> uſe the Torture? And yet no man blameth them for proceeding according to the Law of their Countrey herein; nor yet in their execution, when they break the legs, arms and thighs of the Malefactours, and then fet them upon a wheel on the end of a great pole, there to languiſh to death: an execution far more direfull than the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> preſſing, which is ſo ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly done, and ſo ſeldom uſed. But why doth he not name the Authour of our own or forreign writers, which condemn this kind of execution? Let him do it yet, and he ſhall have moe Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thours of his own Countrey that condemn their courſe of Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: and yet the <hi>Engliſh</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain not of the courſe in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, but of the unlawfull uſe of it; contrarie to the rules of the Laws even of the United Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces. Laſtly, in this point the Authour pretendeth, that little or no Torture was uſed in this proceſs. What the Torture was,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:169753:94"/>and in what degree, appears in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Relation: but he can find little or none mentioned in the Acts. What if he will not find it? or what if their Officers of <hi>Amboyna</hi> have concealed it? ſhall we not believe thoſe that ſuffered it themſelves? ſhall we not believe thoſe, that being themſelves acquitted, yet heard the cries, and ſaw the bodies of <hi>Johnſon, Clark,</hi> and <hi>Tomſon,</hi> and have confirmed their Relation by their corporal Oaths? As for the Act of the five and twentieth of February, which this Authour hath here tranſcribed; it cannot be a true Act: for therein it is ſaid, that that day all the <hi>Engliſh</hi> were examined one by one, and ſome before Torture, and ſome after confeſſed the Fact. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as it appeareth not onely by the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Relation, but by this very Authour in the precedent page, that they were not all exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined the ſame five and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth day of February; but that the examination continued ſix dayes together, even to the third of March incluſive. How then
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:169753:94"/>could the Act of the five and twentieth of February have all their confeſſions? By this may appear, what credit may be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to theſe Acts, or elſe to this Authour. Here alſo by the way he tels us of the deliberation of their Councel; whether the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of the Fact might be reſpited, or the cauſe removed: wherein it was reſolved, that exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution muſt needs be done in the place of the delict, for example ſake; and might not be reſpited, for fear leſt the Conſpiratours (as he tearms them) might have more Dependances than yet were known; and in particular, the <hi>Ternatans</hi> and other <hi>Indians</hi> about <hi>Amboyna.</hi> A poor pretext: as if, having all the <hi>Engliſh</hi> in Irons aboard their ſeveral ſhips, they ſhould need to fear their joyning with the <hi>Ternatans.</hi> But it may be, they feared ſome <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſhips alſo to come thither: for ſo they had made their own people believe. And therefore, two ſhips being deſcried at Sea, the <hi>Dutch</hi> and their free <hi>Burghers</hi> cried out, That there were the <hi>Engliſh</hi> that
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:169753:95"/>ſhould have holpen to take the Caſtle: but when they arrived, they proved to be two ſhips of the <hi>Hollanders</hi> come from <hi>Jac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catra;</hi> wherein was a Letter from the Preſident of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> there, to call away Captain <hi>Towerſon</hi> and all the <hi>Engliſh</hi> from <hi>Amboyna</hi> to <hi>Jaccatra.</hi> Which Letter was opened and read by the <hi>Dutch</hi> Governour, while our people were yet in priſon, and not executed; and might well have ſecured him, that there was no further danger to be feared of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> aids of ſhipping, what-ever the <hi>Engliſh</hi> priſoners had through Torture confeſſed.</p>
                  <p>At laſt the Authour comes to the ſentence it ſelf, tranſcribing out of the Acts of the ninth of March, That the Colledge of Judges being then competent, and calling upon the name of the Lord to aſſiſt them in this mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full aſſembly, to preſide in their hearts, and inſpire them with equity and Juſtice; proceeded to ſentence, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Who knoweth not, but the Act may be thus formed,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:169753:95"/>and yet no prayer at all made? or if there were any ſuch prayer, yet the proceedings well weighed, will ſhew it to be but like <hi>Jeza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels</hi> Faſt, the preparative to the falſe judgement againſt <hi>Naboth.</hi> Neither will the wiſe and indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Judges of this whole mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, conceive the better of the cauſe, for the Hypocritical forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities therein obſerved.</p>
                  <p>Laſt of all, he concludes his treatiſe with a juſtification, yea, an Elogie and commendation of the whole proceedings of the <hi>Dutch</hi> at <hi>Amboyna</hi> againſt the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh;</hi> not finding the leaſt to be blamed to the <hi>Dutch,</hi> but aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vating the crime of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> very ridiculouſly, becauſe (for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth) that this plot amongſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things, was againſt the great means of the <hi>Neatherlands Eaſt-India</hi> Company: as if a conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racie to rob them, (if any ſuch had been) muſt needs be Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, or as if the intent onely in any Crime but treaſon, were Capital.</p>
                  <p>Thus have we examined this ſtrained juſtification of that moſt
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:169753:96"/>Barbarous and execrable proceſs of <hi>Amboyna;</hi> conſiſting of a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amble, full of falſe and forged ſuſpicions; a Narration of the Fact, fraught with ridiculous abſurdities, contrarieties, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſibilities, and of a diſpute of impertinences, with conceal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the main grounds of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> griefs. All which veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth that of <hi>Papinian.</hi> That Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricides are more eaſily commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted than defended.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
               <div type="account">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:169753:96"/>
                  <head>REMARKS upon the fore-going HISTORIE.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O husband the Remainder of theſe Sheets the beſt that I can, to avoid impertinence, which is certainly the ſpeaking of few things in many words (though grave men uſe it) and withall to clear up, or to ſay better, exaggerate one of the moſt criminal Stories that ever was, I preſume to affix what conſiderations of mine I can ſet down; not out of any enmitie to the Nation, nor to rip up old ſoars, nor in
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:169753:97"/>order to provoke a Natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal jealouſie, but upon a clear Intention, to let this Nation ſee, that as by Gods immediate hand, they are reſcued out of the bondage of a Monarchy, ſo in requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal of that mercie, they ought to look to be thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for it. And as he hath provided for them beyond means and hopes, ſo they ought not to be wanting in any thing that may make appear their deteſtation of thoſe offences that are in his eyes of anger, but ſeek by all their power and might, to acquit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
                  <p>For the nature of the plot; you have ſeen what it is, a deſign of a few <hi>Japon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes</hi> to ſurpriſe a Caſtle,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:169753:97"/>whereas in it ſelf, both as they ſtood unfurniſhed with arms, and unſeconded with ſhips, while their enemie was ſtrongly Garrifoned, little better than a ſimple impoſſibilitie, beſides that, there wanted an end to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage and recompence ſuch an attempt; and it is withall to be ſuppoſed, that the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> in a matter of that importance and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, would have choſen o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Confidents than a number of <hi>Japoneſſes,</hi> a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that any reaſonable man might from their barbaritie ſuſpect; and we are to note, that in the examination of the firſt <hi>Japonneſs,</hi> (which was the beginning of the whole proceſs, there were no legal <hi>indicia</hi> found from
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:169753:98"/>him, the behaviour that he uſed, being no other than what may be uſed by any Souldier in the place where he ſerveth, other <hi>indicia</hi> there were none in the leaſt, neither of proviſions of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> for ſuch an attempt, nor of correſpondencies to that purpoſe, nor any other agreeing with the rules and examples given by the law or its expounders. Beſides, it is not enough for to take a confeſſion upon the Rack, God having not ſent all men courage of bodies to endure high tortures (as
<note n="*" place="margin">Collins, Beamont, Sherrock</note> ſome in this tragedie, wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried with ſuffering, bade them propoſe what they would have them confeſs) but it is by Law required, that they ſhould be iterated
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:169753:98"/>and confirmed ſome days after, when the pain of the partie is over, and no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther torment offered unto him. Now in this caſe, there is never a confeſſion entered in the Acts of the Council of <hi>Amboyna,</hi> but it is forced from the parties themſelves by unſupporta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble tortures, not one witneſs being either examined or depoſed. Withall, if there had been as much guilt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Engliſh</hi> as is ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, why did none of them attempt, either to tranſport themſelves in the Curricurries, and other veſſels, that then departed as freely from <hi>Amboyna</hi> as at other times, as it was no hard matter, or ſeek to hide themſelves? a guiltie conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:169753:99"/>being the inſecureſt thing in the world, and the <hi>Japonneſſes</hi> being at that time at the torture.</p>
                  <p>Thus much for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>babilitie of this dangerous machination; now for the le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gallitie of the proceeding of the <hi>Dutch</hi> thereupon, we will ſit down and conſider. The <hi>Engliſh</hi> that were tortured, were ſubject to an abſolute Prince, independent of the <hi>Hollander,</hi> but in league with them: ſo they were friends and companions to the <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landers,</hi> and not ſubjects, and were to be governed by their own Laws, or in caſe an offence given to the <hi>Dutch,</hi> by a joynt Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of both Nations. But the Governour of <hi>Amboy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> took juriſdiction over
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:169753:99"/>them, and therefore the whole proceeding had been illegal, had it been as gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle as it was cruel. Nor is it enough to ſay, that the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of another Countrey, offending againſt a Forreign juriſdiction (under which they are at preſent) ought to be puniſhed by thoſe Laws, for the <hi>Engliſh</hi> had an intereſt and ſhare in the place, and there were, as I ſaid before, as <hi>ſocii,</hi> not as <hi>ſubditi:</hi> not to ſay that there was no offence at all, ſo that the ground of the Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is taken away. Nay, ſuppoſe that we had been under their juriſdiction, yet were the proceedings abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely illegal: For they ſhould have been agreeable to the cuſtom of the <hi>Low-Countreys,</hi>
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:169753:100"/>which thoſe were not, and therefore it was an offence in the Governour, and a high one againſt the laws of his own Countrey. For all penal Laws, ſtrictly circumſtantiate, as well for executing juſt rigour, as for preventing of crueltie; and every Miniſter of Juſtice that tranſgreſſeth herein, as if he behead a man that is adjudged to be hanged, he renders himſelf little better than in the ſame capacitie. Yet notwithſtanding, there was no juſt <hi>indicium</hi> for the torturing of the firſt <hi>Japan,</hi> nor any proofs againſt the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> but forced confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of thoſe tortured wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, which for the moſt part were directed by the <hi>Dutch, in his verbis:</hi> which
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:169753:100"/>ground of Torture is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited by their own Law.</p>
                  <p>For matter of Torture, if you have had the heart to ſurvay it, I ſuppoſe you will think it needs neither heightning, nor ſhadowing, it is ſo foul of it ſelf. For my part all the debauched cruelties of the firſt Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Emperours, when the invention of a good exqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite Torment was a good way for advancement, though ſavage devices in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted upon the Martyrs, when the continuance of perſecution hardened and inſtructed cruelty; all thoſe ſanguinarie Barbariſms of the moſt unciviliz'd Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions have not appeared to me ſo foul and exquiſite as this ſingle proceſs; and that
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:169753:101"/>by a people in league with us, of opinion with us in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and obliged to us in effect for their being, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed by us with the loſs of ſo many brave lives, and the profuſion of ſo much treaſure, even in our own moſt dangerous times, when they were like to be ſwallowed up by a ravenous invader, and ſtood deſerted by all their other neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours; yet theſe men for the engroſſing of that Trade, wherein they have been unhappily fortunate, could cancel all theſe obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations, and break the Laws of nature, nations, and hoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitality to bring it about.</p>
                  <p>And truly me thinks up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this occaſion, I cannot but look back on the feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:169753:101"/>of thoſe times, the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the Honour of that Prince that could ſleep ſo ſoundly, when ſuch cries were ſo loud in his ears. This it is to be under the Government of <hi>one,</hi> who notwithſtanding is govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by a <hi>Pimp</hi> or a <hi>Paraſite,</hi> who though he have ſuch a ſacred truſt as the ſafety and the righting of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, yet to pleaſe his <hi>Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit,e</hi> and the better to ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to his luſt and luxurie, would be blind to ſuch a violation of his own Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and the ſafety of his people, while the bloud cries in vain behind the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, and ſo becomes entayl'd on his own head, and for ought we know, may ſtill lie
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:169753:102"/>upon ours. But the <hi>Dutch</hi> knew well enough what an eaſie and ſecure Prince they had to deal with, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore like crafty Foxes ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventured to play tricks with the old drowſie Lion; they knew well enough that the exorbitancies, prodigalities, and ill proviſions of that Court would ever keep it beggarly and needy, and that there wanted not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments in it that Gold would work upon: and therefore they had old <hi>Jammy</hi> faſt enough beſieg'd (though he were a place eaſie enough to take in of himſelf) ſo that this buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs was huſhed up in ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence for a little money, and the cautionarie Towns were ſold for <hi>nine pence,</hi> which
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:169753:102"/>had coſt us a <hi>Noble,</hi> they themſelves laughing at the credulitie of that ſtupid Prince, that would give up ſo conſiderable places (which held them in aw, and preſerved us ever a good means to right our ſelves) and thinking ſo great a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter-piece, that their engine, the <hi>then</hi> Secretarie, had a preſent of no leſs than 30. or 40000. <hi>l.</hi> for that one ſervice. But the beſt of it is, the enchantment is now broke up, and we begin to rouſe our ſelves again, and with the bleſſing of God upon our Liberty, may ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive at a higher pitch of glorie and happineſs than any of our Anceſtors? if they, that have overcome, ſheath their ſwords (as God
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:169753:103"/>be thanked they do) and they that are overcome lay aſide their hates, as I wiſh they may. For ſo we ſhall grow up to be one body, and ſhall be formidable to all round about us, and be able rather to right our di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed Neighbours, than be in a capacity to receive injuries of the leaſt, much leſs of the moſt horrid na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
